It's the early 1970s.
And a force is sweeping through rock
with a sound big enough
to fill football stadiums.
Its name, Led Zeppelin.
A group that will become the first
gladiators of Stadium Rock.
# It's been a long time
since I rock-and-rolled
since I did the Stroll
# Ooh, let me get it back,
let me get it back, let me get it back
# mm-baby, where I come from
For the next 20 years,
stadium rock will be an elite club
with only a handful of
ambitious bands can hope to join.
Do you believe in rock 'n roll?
For this groups,
size really does matter.
It is arrogance
with a cock.
These are performers who specialize
in driving audiences wild.
It's the greatest job in the world!
But they will discover through
a global stadium rock show
that their music isn't just being
listened to around the world
but might also help change it.
We had the whole planet.
And it turns out that
the 'lingua franca' of the world
is not English,
it's rock 'n roll.
This is the story
of the age of Stadium Rock.
When a succession of great artists
took the music
onto a global stage
and played for the higher
stakes possible.
You are sort of like
the Aztec Sun Prince.
You're there in your palace
but you know
when the year's up,
the priest is gonna come,
drag you out, take you up the pyramid
and cut your heart out with a knife.
# ...of the world.
# There's a lady who's sure
all that glitters is gold
# And she's buying a stairway to heaven
Led Zeppelin came to America
at the end of the 60s,
and by 1973 were playing to audiences
of over 50,000 people.
On stage, singer Robert Plant,
combined power and intimacy
to create a magical vibe
that defined stadium rock.
# And she's buying
a stairway to heaven
Great stadium rock is really
about the universal.
It's about having those songs
that the whole world wants to sing.
Sometimes it lacks the subtlety
and refinement that gets critics excited
and they tend to be quite
harsh about stadium rock,
it's almost become
a term of abuse.
And yet, the great stadium rock bands
take it beyond a big show,
they take it into the realm
of spirit and substance.
But I've got some good news.
Listen!
# If there's a bustle in your hedgerow,
don't be alarmed now,
# It's just a spring clean
for the May Queen
I remember seeing Led Zeppelin
and it was really a religious experience.
It was so perfect,
and so much everything that I would
ever want to aspire to be.
Backstage, Zeppelin's manager,
Peter Grunt,
scourge of concert
promoters around the world,
would be working
his own kind of magic.
Don't fucking talk to me,
it's my bloody act!
I think I'll leave you anytime. You
couldn't even give them a starting line.
You are the fucking controller
of the thing, aren't you?
For concert promoters, Grunt was
an intimidating and infamous figure.
But he would have a lasting
impact on the business of rock.
You rented it and you controlled it.
Isn't selling fucking
pirate posters.
Led Zeppelin were a monumentally
important band.
They literally changed the economics.
They said, we'll take 90%
and you'll keep 10%,
to the promoters,
which was an inversion
of the way it had always worked.
And they had the nerve
and the toughness to do it.
And they were such a powerful draw,
that having 10% of Led Zeppelin
was still worth it to the promoters.
The big bands of the era
followed Zeppelin's lead,
both The Who and The Rolling Stones
found the emphasis of their career
shifting from making records
to filling the largest spaces possible.
These were, as it were,
slightly old guard,
these were people who had been
big towards the end of the 1960s.
But they in turn inspired
new generations.
# I see a little silhouette of a man
# Scaramouch, scaramouch
will you do the fandango
# Thunderbolt and lightning
- very very frightening me
# Gallileo, Gallileo, Gallileo, Gallileo,
Gallileo Figaro - magnifico
1975 was the year the group Queen
emerged onto the world's stage.
'Bohemian Rhapsody' brought comparisons
with the epics of Led Zeppelin.
On tour in Japan, they were hailed
as visiting gods.
We got on the plane, a young,
up-and-coming, hopeful group in England,
and we got off the plane in Tokyo
like The Beatles.
It was very...
blindingly strange.
# Oh mama mia, mama mia,
mama mia let me go
We're completely overwhelmed
by what's happened since we came here.
It's never happened to us
in any other country.
Most groups, at that point,
were very much against
putting on any kind of show.
It was very much like,
let's get into our music, man,
and everything else
can take a back seat.
We weren't like that.
We thought, "No. We entertain people."
# A baby I was when you took my hand
# And the light of
the night burned bright
# And the people all
stared didn't understand
# But you knew my name on sight
Queen's live act was centered
around singer Freddy Mercury,
one of the greatest frontmen
in the history of rock.
People actually believed
when he first used to come on sort of...
Hell thunderbolts!
And we used to dress somebody up
as Freddy and just flash a light,
and now I'm here,
now I'm there,
and of course,
one of them was him.
It seemed almost
like a magic show.
The thing about it that
I loved mostly was that
he wasn't asking your permission,
he simply was saying,
this is who I am,
take it or leave it.
That's what rock...
It's putting your chin out and say,
"Go ahead, take your best shot."
Queen's show always ended
with the audience demanding more.
And it was this ritual
which inspired Brian May
to write the most famous
stadium anthem of them all.
There was a place called
Bingley Hall, near Birmingham,
which we used to play,
and one night it was packed
and heaving and sweaty.
It was an amazing gig.
And when we came off
they didn't stop singing.
They were singing to us.
They were singing
'You'll never walk alone'.
And we all looked at
each other and thought,
"Something is really happening here.
This is a complete interaction."
And that night I woke up
in the middle of the night
thinking, what would an audience do
if you gave them permission,
what would they do.
They could stand, they could clap,
they could sing something
which made them feel they were
bonded together,
something which made them
feel strong.
# We will, we will rock you
Come on! Sing it everybody!
I think it was very stripped down
bareness of it.
It was just sort of
caught people.
You know, "Rock!"
When it was played live,
'We will rock you' would segue
into a song of Freddy Mercury's,
the equally bombastic,
'We are the Champions'.
# We are the champions, my friend
# And we'll keep on fighting
till the end
The songs would provide
an explosive concert finale
for the rest of Queen's career.
'We will rock you' and
'We are the champions'
are triumphalist rock songs.
It is all about the communication,
the empathy, the energy exchange,
between thousands of people
in a stadium
and that larger-than-life
character on the stage.
# We are the champions
That is the essence of stadium rock.
# No time for losers,
'cause we are the champions...
# of the world.
The sports arenas of the USA
were stadium rock spiritual home.
And both 'We will rock you' and
'We are the champions'
became an eternal part
of their culture.
It was in the 1970s
that American bands created
a brand of theatrical rock
purpose-built for these venues.
Kiss! Kiss! Kiss!
American stadium rock is really
just rock as grand entertainment.
In America you get
a tradition that gives you Aerosmith,
and ultimately gives you Bon Jovi.
Or it gives you Kiss.
Just the theater of rock
without any substance.
# You show us everything you've got
# You keep on dancin
and the room gets hot
# You drive us wild,
we'll drive you crazy
Kiss were four glam rock fans
who hit upon the idea
of using makeup
to transform themselves into
larger-than-life rock stars.
The plan was to create an illusion.
Because if you can get people
to believe what they're seeing
is more than what it is,
it becomes more than it is.
# I wanna rock and roll all nite
and party every day
Kiss were hated by
music critics,
but built up a fan base of millions,
because their shows could successfully
entertain tens of thousands of people.
It's not spontaneous.
Everything is scripted.
The focus is not necessarily
on the music.
The frontman basically
is barely playing.
He misses more notes than he hits.
The emphasis is on the spectacle.
I could care less whether
'New Musical Express'
or some other music magazine
believes that what we do is valid.
A billion dollars later,
they can kiss my ass, baby!
The band was deliberately marketed
outside the ghetto
of hardcore rock fans.
This is Kiss.
Each sold separately.
And you can put them
in any crazy pose you want.
They were, with the Kiss dolls,
appealing to people who were 4.
Literally they had no relationship
to rock music,
they would not be able
to say what rock music was
and they may have owned
the Kiss dolls.
They blow fire and spit blood and...
- And that's neat, uh?
- Yeah.
At their peak, Kiss earned $50 million
a year from merchandise alone.
Their products could be found
everywhere.
Even in the dressing room of the man
who would eventually deliver
stadium rock from this glam
and platform heel phase,
Bruce Springsteen.
Bruce Springsteen was one
of the first people viewed as
being necessary to save
rock 'n roll.
He was a good looking guy,
writing great songs,
who seemed, more than anything else,
relentlessly sincere.
He is the 70s rock Dylan.
# Don't run back inside,
# you know just what I'm here for
# So you're scared and you're thinking
# That maybe we ain't
that young anymore
# Show a little faith
there's magic in the night
# You ain't a beauty but hey
you're alright
# And that's alright with me
# You can hide 'neath your covers
and study your pain
Bruce Springsteen and his group
the E Street Band,
had no need for costumes
or pyrotechnics.
Songs like 'Thunder Road'
were widescreen tales
of escape and freedom.
The honesty of the music
he played...
You know, there wasn't a lot of fanfare
and smoke and mirrors and bullshit.
It was some guys
on that stage,
putting their heart and soul
into what they were doing.
# Except roll down the window
# And let the wind blow
back your hair
# Well the night's busting open
# These two lanes
will take us anywhere
# We got one last chance
to make it real
# To trade in these wings
on some wheels
# Climb in back
# Heaven's waiting on down the tracks
Springsteen wore his heart
on his sleeve,
but also tapped into the common
experiences of a generation
coming of age in America
in the 1970s.
That moment in the 70s
was a moment of crashed
expectations in America.
We were told there was no more
oil on the ground.
The speed limit had been
dropped to 55
and Watergate and the fall of Vietnam
were just the icing on the cake.
From now on it's just gonna be
work in a rotten job
for not enough money
and inflation's going wild,
and you're never gonna be able
to have your own house.
It was just like,
"The fun is over!"
# It's town full of losers
# And I'm pulling out of here to win
Springsteen came out
of the music scene
centered around the troubled
New Jersey resort of Asbury Park.
A town scarred by race
riots at the start of the 1970s,
and in a downward spiral.
I was a loner.
I didn't really fit in very well,
and so it was through music
that I fundamentally connected
myself to my world,
to the world that was out there.
I had my... where my ideas
and my actions had some impact.
It was basically street music.
That's where it came from.
In 1975, Springsteen had been
a struggling figure
on the verge of being dropped
by his record label.
But with the album and single
'Born to Run'
he turned his career round
in unprecedented fashion.
I knew when I heard that song,
ok, we have a whole new
thing going on here.
This is not just a song,
this is a movie soundtrack.
# In the day we sweat it out in
the streets of a runaway American dream
# At night we ride through mansions
of glory in suicide machines
# Sprung from cages out on highway 9,
# Chrome wheeled, fuel injected
# and steppin' out over the line
# Baby this town rips
the bones from your back
# It's a death trap, it's a suicide rap
# We gotta get out while we're young
# 'Cause tramps like us,
baby we were born to run
'Born to Run', a street anthem
song with real passion,
turned Springsteen into the most
talked about performer in America.
Bruce really was
uncomfortable with it.
He wanted it but not that way.
He wanted it more in his own terms.
He wanted it to go a little slower.
It seemed that it was
getting out of hand for him.
When 'Born to Run' hit,
Springsteen was still playing theaters,
places that held no more
than 2000 people.
Now, as a star turn,
he could fill arenas,
venues that held up to 20,000.
But Springsteen drew back,
fearful of losing his personal
connection with the audience.
He seemed to be really weary
of taking any steps too fast.
He stayed in clubs
when he could be filling theaters.
He stayed in theaters for a long time
when he could be playing arenas.
He didn't move to arenas until
he really knew he could do it right.
You're trying to get around
to as many cities as you can.
That's what's best for the fans.
Yeah, you can stay in a club,
and play that club
30 nights in a row,
or you can play 6 nights
in the theater,
or one night in the arena,
you know what I mean?
# Rosalita jump a little lighter
# Señorita come sit by my fire
# I just want to be
your love, ain't no lie
# Rosalita you're my stone desire
It was on his first major
arena tour in 1978
that Springsteen learnt
to love the big stage.
When he went out there
and it felt good,
it was a delight to him.
He figured out that size was not
the obstacle that he thought it was.
That the shape of the building
was not the issue.
It was the shape of the music
and the shape of what he projected.
And you could see it worked.
The band's three hour set
would climax with the song 'Rosalita'.
Springsteen used it as an opportunity
to pull out every stop.
It just did everything, you know.
It's all this big story,
it was funny, it was silly.
There were many different arrangemental
things that just simply
was meant to drive you crazy.
By the end of the 70s
it was becoming clear
that stadium rock could embrace
both the blue-collar epics of Springsteen
and the camp theatrics
of Kiss and Queen.
But on the streets of London
a group had formed who would
broaden stadium rock even more
by bringing their own
global take to the music,
The Police.
# Roxanne, you don't have
to put on the red light
# Those days are over
# You don't have to sell
your body to the night
The Police are significant because
they actually did bring
a new sound to stadium rock.
That there was a reggae tinge to it
was different because
when you talk about stadium rock,
you are talking about rock;
this are white guys with guitars.
Now, The Police were white
guys with guitars,
but they had also clearly heard
a few reggae records in their time.
# Roxanne, you don't have
to put on the red light
Stewart Copeland had founded
The Police in 1977,
along with base
playing frontman, Sting.
They were soon joined
by guitarist Andy Summers.
The exotic rhythms that propelled
The Police's early classic, 'Roxanne',
came naturally to Copeland,
who'd grown up in the Middle East.
# Roxanne, you don't have
to put on the red light
Since I grew up with backward rhythm,
our rhythms were slightly out of kelter.
Instead of... Roxanne
It was Roxanne...
# Roxanne, you don't have
to wear that dress tonight
The base, which goes...
move it over one beat,
so it goes...
Real simple.
'Roxanne' was first released
in April, 1978,
but would not be an immediate hit.
The British music scene
was dominated by punk
and 'Roxanne' simply didn't fit in.
A lot of the hacks then
just wouldn't give us a shot.
We were just about finished
as a band, you know,
we couldn't get gigs really.
If we got a gig, we'd have to spend
all the money hiring the PA
and the van to get there.
As a last roll of the dice,
The Police decided to chance their luck
with a self-financed American tour.
It felt different when
we came to the US.
It felt like it was a clean slate.
People accepted us just
on the music alone.
They didn't care about punk
credentials or anything like that.
They just reacted to the music.
# And all this guilt will be on your head
# I guess you'd call it suicide
# But I'm too full to swallow my pride
# I can't, I can't, I can't stand losing
They responded to our music,
and just city by city,
incrementally, tour after tour.
You know, people imagine that
it happened suddenly. It wasn't.
It was a lot of shows.
It was step by step by step.
They drove around in a van.
They played every crappy bar
and kept coming back, and back, and back.
I knew people who thought
The Police were from Boston,
because they played in the New York
to Boston corridor so much.
The Police at the far corner
of the store, here to say "hello".
Come over to meet them...
The group's progress in the US
immediately reflected back
in their British record sales.
And within a year of going
to America
the band would be
a number one act in the UK.
But Stewart's brother, Miles,
the group's manager,
had a plan that would take them global.
There were two things that
were really important.
Number one is, when you
interview the group,
most groups had the same
thing to say.
How did you get your name,
what did you do,
it was always the same story.
Yeah, we formed this
little group and friends
we went playing at the Marquee Club
and we did this and that...
I heard that one before, ok?
So, to put the group in situation
where they've done something
nobody else has done,
means that any time they do
an interview,
the interviews are much
more interesting.
Secondly, if you would
put them in a situation
where the photographs
are gonna be interesting.
You've got a picture of them in Delhi
wearing maharaja suits,
you go, "Wow! The Police are touring
the world. My God! They're in India.
"They're in Egypt. They're... God!"
It just created this mystique
of excitement.
The Police's 1980 world tour
saw them play countries
where few Western rock acts
had ever performed.
# I can't, I can't, I can't stand losing
This morning we left Bombay
and we will be landing in Cairo
in about three hours.
I think we should just... get off,
you know, let's go.
It was fantastic fun.
Everywhere was total mayhem
as we went around and enjoyed this
but as well as the fun of it
it was very press worthy.
It's nice to be here in Athens.
By 1981, The Police had built
an international following,
and the band's enormous potential
was starting to be recognised
by the rock establishment.
Freddy was very taken, you know.
And he got hold of a video
of The Police and said,
"Look. Look at this guy. Look at Sting.
Look what a showman he is.
"This guy is gonna be the next
whatever it is, you know."
The Police were not the only ones looking
beyond Britain and America for success.
Having scored an American #1 with
'Crazy Little Thing Called Love",
Queen received an offer
to play in South America,
a continent totally ignored
by the big rock bands.
I remember they guy who
wanted to promote us,
he came over and said,
"Look, I tell you.
"You can play football
stadiums down here",
and we went, "Yeah, come on...
Argentina, Brazil, they've
never heard of us. "
And he says, "No. I promise you you will
fill football stadiums everywhere you go."
Fred, how do you feel playing
and singing before 200,000 people?
I haven't done it yet.
# Another one bites the dust
The tour would take them
to Argentina and Brazil,
countries then under
military dictatorships.
# Another one bites the dust
There was a great fear among
governments that
a large number of people gathered together
would be a dangerous force politically.
# How do you think
I'm going to get along
# Without you when you're gone
There was a sort of squad of military
in front of the stage,
a lot of rifles everywhere and
so we raised the English and
the Argentinean flags simultaneously
each side of the stage.
In only a few years time, stadium rock
would align itself with political causes.
But for now, Freddy Mercury
had a more old fashioned idea
of the role of the entertainer.
He was completely apolitical.
And he was always insistent on the fact
that we had nothing to do with politics.
We should stay out of it completely
and hopefully thereby above it.
By the time the tour
reached Brazil
they were playing to over
130,000 people.
Their stadium moment
had arrived
and the band connected
with their huge audiences
in a spectacular way.
# Hurry back hurry back,
# Don't take it away from me,
# Because you don't know
what it means to me
That experience in Argentina
and Brazil echoes down now.
Generally if I meet someone
in the street
and they get very emotional and teary,
and want to put their arms around me,
usually it's an Argentinean
or a Brazilian.
And I feel the same...
all that feeling comes back,
an amazing bond that we had
in South America at that time.
# I want to break free
It was just as well
that Queen had built up
an enormous fan base in South America,
in the US their career
would go into rapid decline.
Largely as a result of one
of their videos.
# I've got to break free
# God knows
# God knows I want to break free
I was out there at the time
doing some interviews
and I remember when you put
this video on people would go suddenly
blanche.
And go, "Well, we'll move swiftly on."
As if the fact that we dressed up
as girls and lampooned Coronation Street
they just didn't get the joke.
A lot of America really wasn't
ready for that kind of thing.
And they dropped the record
like a stone.
# I don't want to live alone
Freddy did say, "Well, I don't
know about America.
"I suppose I'll have to fucking die
before we get to be there again."
And, you know...
not far off really.
As Queen discovered to their cost,
it was essential to understand
the American market.
And in the early 80s, few were better
at this than The Police.
In 1983, they delivered a record
that would take America by storm.
# Every breath you take
# Every move you make
# Every bond you break,
every step you take
# I'll be watching you
We all knew that it was a hit.
We all knew that
that was the best song
Sting had every written
up until that point.
He had a knack of writing a song
that ostensibly was about this,
but you listen closely to the lyrics
and really it's about that.
You know, it's a song about
voyeurism and stalking,
but it sounds like a love song.
# Oh, can't you see
# You belong to me
'Every Breath You Take' became
The Police's first American #1,
and the band embarked
on a 9 month tour
that saw them played
the most hallowed turf in rock,
Shea Stadium, where The Beatles
had performed to 56,000 people in 1965.
In 1983, The Police played
to over 70,000.
I remember walking out
introducing the group,
and I go, "Ladies and gentlemen.
And now..."
And the place erupted.
And I'm hearing this "Oahhhh!" from
the crowd, you could feel the wind of this.
And you're thinking, "Oh my God!"
These guys are gonna
have that for 2 hours.
This is called 'Synchronicity'.
It is an incredible buzz.
You just feel this very positive
energy coming towards you.
It's like... a wave.
You kind of absorb it.
It's very empowering.
It's a great experience.
It's a drug.
Shea Stadium sold out
within hours
and the show marked
the coronation of The Police
as the new kings
of stadium rock.
That's when we went
into the stratosphere.
At that point we're no longer the
cutting edge of the latest new thing.
We now own America.
The Police were now in a position
to enjoy the spoils of their victory.
# Giant steps are what you take
walking on the moon
We would finish the last song
and three limousines are
right up against the stage.
And my limousine has my cold drinks,
my towels, everything I need,
'cause I come off soaking wet, I mean,
just heart pounding, head exploding.
The t-shirt salesmen, they're just
having money throwed at them.
10 dollar bills, 15... they make change,
and the money goes into a big trash bin.
They grab all those bags of loot
and throw them on the plane with us.
As it's taking off we can see
that whole part of the state
that's just jammed with cars trying
to get out of the stadium.
And we throw the bags like that and
it was just like Ebenezer Scrooge
swimming in his money,
I swear to God
it was a green blizzard in our plane.
The 'Synchronicity' world tour
saw the band play to millions of fans
at over a hundred shows.
We were a huge cash cow
while it was going,
so we're like the three treasures
protected inside a fortress.
I was saying to Stewart the other day,
it's like you sort of return to the
mind of a child, you become very simple.
Every move you make you're
sort of catered to it.
What's that over there?
Whatever it is they'll bring it here
so I can have a look at it.
I want a... and there's
three guys going, "What?"
And I want a... string quartet.
And I began to feel that
I was loosing my ability to
be a human being in the human world.
There's only one way
to get out of there,
which was the meltdown
of the golden cage.
# In my life,
yeah, yeah,
Sting was talking about possibly
to end the band.
I think at that point we were
so confused and glutted with it all
that we went "Oh, yeah, yeah.
Let's end it all."
What a great idea.
By the time the tour came
to an end in 1984,
The Police had decided
to call it a day.
The Police peaked at a time
when the record industry was booming.
Gorged on multi-platinum records
by Michael Jackson, Prince, and others.
Every major artist would
have to work out
how to navigate this brave
new blockbuster world.
And Bruce Springsteen
was no different.
John Landau, his manager and producer,
was pushing him to really go out,
and one time try to be
as far reaching, as successful,
as blockbuster as he could be.
The stadiums were beckoning Bruce.
But first, he needed a killer single
that would prepare the way.
"Ok, what is the single?"
Well, you listen to the radio
and say, ok, that's what's going on
and you try, basically, to do your
version of what might fit in to that.
# I get up in the evening
'Dancing in the Dark' was the lead single
for the new album 'Born in the USA'.
It had a rhythm track influenced
by Michael Jackson
and Bruce even consented to appear
in his first proper video.
At last, Springsteen
was willing to see
just how far he could go.
# Hey there, baby
I could use just a little help
# You can't start a fire
without a spark
# This gun's for hire
# Even if we're just
dancing in the dark
At that point I said, "Well, I'm here,
let me see what happens,
"let me see where it goes,
let me see what my limitations are."
You know, you take the ride...
I would have regretted terribly
if I felt like I had that opportunity
and hadn't made the most of it,
or hadn't taken it
to where I thought I could.
'Born in the USA' would become one of
the most successful records of the 1980s.
Its songs dominated the American
charts for nearly two years.
It had a ridiculous, ridiculous fate
of having seven top ten singles.
To promote the album, Springsteen
embarked on a 15-month world tour
*** him finally move up
to play stadiums.
The first day, one of the things we did*,
we were outside, in day time,
so you could see the massive
audience we had.
And that was kind of good fun.
# Born down in a dead man's town
# The first kick I took
was when I hit the ground
The title track, 'Born in the USA',
would be Springsteen's
most controversial song.
Behind the all American swagger
its lyrics spoke of darkness
and disillusion.
# Born in the USA
# (I was) Born in the USA
In that song Bruce had encapsulated
the frustration, bitterness
and the disappointment
of so many of the people we'd met
who'd served in the Vietnam War.
# And so they put a rifle in my hands
# Sent me off to a foreign land
# To go and kill the yellow man
A lot of people misred the lyrics,
and Reagan was king at that point.
Everybody thought this was
a nationalistic pro-Reagan song,
that was good for 5-6
million probably, you know.
Amongst those who misinterpreted
the song was Reagan himself.
America's future rests in a thousand
dreams inside your hearts.
If rests in the message of hope
in songs of a man
so many young Americans admire,
New Jersey's own Bruce Springsteen.
You gotta laugh.
You realise you clueless these people
that are in charge of things are.
He doesn't know who Bruce Springsteen is,
I'm surprised he didn't say
Bruce Springstine or
something, who knows?
I probably could've made a record
that would've been
more easily understood but
it wouldn't have been as good.
The record is right on the money.
There may be some misinterpretations
of it out there, you know,
but it was the right record.
'Born in the USA' would go on
to sell over 15 million copies in America.
President Reagan was not the only
person buying into the idea of Bruce,
the most ordinary mega-star
on the planet.
Well, he's one of us.
He's part of New Jersey.
He loves Philadelphia,
he really does.
He's the boss, you know, we call him
'the boss' and he is the boss.
The people who really love
Springsteen, the real believers,
they think that when Springsteen
is not in the studio or on tour,
he actually goes back to New Jersey
and works in a car wash.
So he becomes this idea,
this impossible idea
that makes him messianic.
He wasn't putting on
an act or anything,
he really was a kind
of regular guy.
And the fact that he was
commercially successful
was simply a matter of greatness
as far as I'm concerned.
That's it.
For all of 'Born in the USA's
huge success
in the overheated rock industry
of the 1980s
other artist's albums
were selling even more.
The numbers were vast.
And even Dire Straits,
fronted by unassuming Geordie
Mark Knopfler,
suddenly discovered they were one of
the most popular groups in the world.
# ... and alarm
# You did not desert me
# My brothers in arms
I love the fact that any stuff
that I may have done
has influenced so many
kids around the world,
because it just happened
to be in front of them.
It's not because it was
good or anything
it was just because it was
in front of them.
And that's what happens.
And you just take your little place
in the chain.
# I want my MTV
Dire Straits' 1985 album
'Brothers in Arms'
would sell over 30 million copies.
In large part this was thanks
to a monster single,
the unforgettable
'Money for Nothing'.
That's the secret
of the whole thing.
It's just to do with
the picking.
# Now look at them yo-yos
that's the way you do it
# You play the guitar on the MTV
# That ain't workin'
that's the way you do it
# Money for nothin' and
the chicks for free
'Money for Nothing' was a wry
commentary on the slick world of MTV
and the 80s music industry.
But with the song's success,
Mark Knopfler soon took his place
in the world he was satirizing.
Everybody wanted to see us.
Everybody wanted to have the records.
You reach a kind of critical mass.
It is not a normal existence.
There were certainly periods
where I'd be probably drinking too much,
probably having my personality
smacked about a bit
by the size of events.
The 'Brothers in Arms' tour
saw Dire Straits play 248 shows
in 117 different cities.
They packed out Wembley Arena
for 13 nights.
# Here comes Johnny
singing oldies, goldies
# Be-Bop-A-Lula, Baby What I Say
# Here comes Johnny
singing I Gotta Woman
# Down in the tunnels,
trying to make it pay
# He got the action, he got the motion
# Oh Yeah the boy can play
# Dedication devotion
# Turning all the night time
into the day
# He do the song about
the sweet lovin' woman
# He do the song about the knife
# He do the walk, he do the walk of life,
yeah he do the walk of life
The sheer scale of the success
enjoyed by Dire Straits and others
at the height of the 80s music boom
would have an important consequence.
The market for rock music
had a huge booming from the mid 80s.
Loads of people benefited from that,
lots of artists benefited from that,
and you could say a degree
of guilt came with that.
A sense of, we have this popularity,
we have this audience, this platform.
Is all we're going to do with it
just sell more records and tickets,
or can we, should we do
something more?
'Money for nothing
and chicks for free',
that's the chorus of one
of their songs.
But their hearts are in helping
to feed those who are starving...
and making great music.
From London, Dire Straits!
On July 13th, 1985,
Dire Straits were in the middle
of their run at Wembley Arena,
but took time out to play a charity show
over in Wembley Stadium,
that would be seen on TV
by a third of the world's population.
We just turned up to do
the gig as normal.
We walked across the car park
to do 'Live Aid',
but somebody said, there's 700 million
people watching or something,
and you just think to yourself,
"Wow! I hope I don't mess up. "
Dire Straits did far from mess up.
They took to the stage with Sting
who sang the intro to 'Money for Nothing'
as he had on the record.
# I want my, I want my MTV
'Live Aid' marked the moment
when the biggest names in rock
realised the could mobilise
a global audience in a call to action.
What music does,
it's still the Pied Piper.
The Pied Piper didn't get the rats
out of the sewers,
or whatever he did lead
them to the thing,
it was the music which drew them
to the river to be drowned.
And so rock 'n roll was
globalisation's Pied Piper
and it summoned people
to the electronic hearth,
this was the world's fireplace now,
the television.
Queen were one group Bob Geldof
wanted on board,
but the band's Roger Taylor had warned
him that Freddy Mercury would be reluctant
to mix music and politics.
Rog said to me that
Fred won't want to do it,
so I didn't sell it
as a political thing to Queen.
I said, "Fred, of any band in
all the world, of any artist,
"you were born for this stage.
You. Darling of the world!"
# Buddy you're a boy make a big noise
# Playin' in the street gonna be
a big man some day
# You got mud on yo' face
# You big disgrace
# Kickin' your can all over the place
- Sing it!
# We will we will rock you
# All we hear is Radio ga ga
# Radio goo goo
# Radio ga ga
We just put our heads down
played hard and let Freddy
strut his stuff.
He just managed to dominate,
seize the... Wembley,
and take it over and conduct.
# Someone still loves you!
I don't know if it was just me,
but I thought Queen,
and this is your old pub-punk-rocker,
I thought Queen were amazing.
And I think that's when
they specifically marked their stamp
as one of the greatest
rock 'n roll bands in their own right.
# We are the champions
# Of the world
'Live Aid' would also be
an important watershed for U2,
the last great band to emerge
from stadium rock's golden age.
# It puts my back up,
puts my back up against the wall
# Sunday, Bloody Sunday
During their second number,
lead singer Bono would make his mark
with a gesture of high drama.
Bono, in his need to reach out
and touch the audience
which he'd been doing
in smaller venues and in theaters.
You know, he'd always go
running off to do...
this thing that he used to do,
which was to drag somebody up and dance.
Springsteen used to do
the same thing as well.
Probably a trick that he'd picked up
from Springsteen.
He decided to do that
at Wembley Stadium...
It took several minutes,
but Bono ended up with a ten-second
clinch surrounded by photographers.
The images of his embrace
were seen all around the world.
Bono had provided
the perfect TV moment,
and that was a TV event.
It wasn't an ordinary live concert.
All their albums were back
into the charts.
And that led on to 'The Joshua Tree',
the biggest album of their career,
and the moment when they became
the biggest band in the world.
If 'Live Aid' had given stadium rock
a conscience,
with 'The Joshua Tree' U2 would
be the ones who would keep it alive.
Behind the album's iconic imagery
they along held belief
in music with a message.
The total package together
spoke of something serious and austere.
And kind of heavy.
# And I can see those fighter planes
# I can see those fighter planes
# Across the mud huts where
the children sleep
# Through the alleys of
a quiet city street
# You take the staircase
to the first floor
At the heart of 'The Joshua Tree'
was the song 'Bullet the Blue Sky',
a direct response to the Reagan
Administration's
covert military operations
in Central America.
# Outside is America
U2's outspokenness made the media
sit up and take notice.
But for many stadium rock bands
the music was the message.
The bands that were emerging
in the 80s, apart from U2,
seemed almost like designer
stadium bands.
Bon Jovi take the formula of Bruce
Springsteen and reduce it to a pop rock.
They lead into to Guns 'n Roses,
it's just all empty bombast.
Big had become sort of synonymous
with something bland,
and so probably U2 felt it tainting
them through their seriousness,
their perceived seriousness.
As the 80s became the 90s,
U2 decided it was time
to lighten up their image.
When they came to tour their
futuristic 1991 album, 'Achtung Baby',
the band entrusted lighting
designer, Willie Williams,
with the task of dreaming up the most
elaborate stadium rock show yet seen,
'Zoo TV'.
It became clear that where
we were going had to be
something on a scale that
hadn't been seen before.
And I was really pushing for
a video art installation on stage
in which they could perform.
What they put together was
the most extravagant
multi-media experience.
It felt like an absolute
technological 'splend'.
Zoo TV used its video screens
as the focus of the show
that was a dark celebration
of the modern world.
Let's see what we've got on TV.
The stage set projected
films and slogans
and could even pick up
local TV stations.
What is this?
Soap operas?
Behind Zoo TV sensory overload
was a belief that stadium rock
could do more than merely entertain.
It could challenge, provoke or change
the way an audience looked at the world.
U2 are artists with a mission.
To them a mass audience is a repository
of potential for good.
And a great artist can reach
into that audience
and can pull out something better,
if you like,
artistically and morally.
The band would even conduct live
satellite links with their own reporter
in the then besieged city
of Sarajevo.
There's about 10 to 15 thousand
refugees that are being
attacked by artillery
and they have nowhere to go.
But music remained the core
of the show.
After an audiovisual assault,
U2 introduced something
new in stadium rock,
the B-Stage, where they performed
an intimate set,
totally surrounded
by the audience.
# It was a cold and wet December day
# When we touched the ground at JFK
# Snow was melting on the ground
# On BLS I heard the sound
# Of an angel
# New York, like a Christmas tree
# Tonight this city belongs to me
# Angel
With Zoo TV, U2 had created
the ultimate stadium rock show.
U2 were the only act that
I can remember seeing
who really were great
in a football stadium.
You go to see the Stones
and they do it,
but you'd much rather see
them in an arena,
you'd much rather see them
in Madison Square Garden
than see them at Giants Stadium.
U2 actually made the stadium work.
U2 are the best stadium rock band
that's ever been.
It doesn't mean they're
the best rock band's ever been,
but they have the ambition
to fill those spaces with something...
truly remarkable and new
and challenging.
Everybody who saw Zoo knows
they'll never see the likes of that again.
Transcription and
synchronization by Fry.