# We don't need no education
On June the 17th, 1981,
"The Wall" came crashing down
on London's Earl's Court
ending the most ambitious rock
extravaganza the world had ever seen.
It just always seemed
like a good idea
to give people something a bit
more theatrical and dramatic
than four guys on stage
playing instruments and singing.
#...leave the kids alone.
Pink Floyd were of a new generation
who believed that rock had
no boundaries musically or visually.
Everything was possible.
It was an amazing amalgam
of different tools in media.
Nobody'd done that at the time.
You feel the repercussions now... still.
# So where were the spiders
Whole new worlds were created as rock
pushed on into unexplored territory.
Within arts generally, there's always
the feeling that one has to innovate
and reevaluate and then move on.
So it happened in rock.
#...and should we crush
his sweet hands?
# Make me a deal and make it straight
# All signed and sealed, I´ll take it
Out went the rule book,
and in came a spirit of experiment.
As opposed to just here's the voice,
here's the chorus, here's the solo,
and here's the bridge,
and then good night.
It was all kind of... you didn't
know what was gonna happen next.
# ...tryin' to make the big time.
# I know what I like...
No longer was it boy meets girl,
now it was boy meets ideas.
The gates had been kicked open.
It was a childhood, you know,
it was exploration, experimentation,
and sniff and smell everything.
From its simple beginnings,
rock had become theatrical spectacle
on a grand scale.
This was a musical earthquake
that was to shake every
rock act that followed.
This was the Second Age of Rock.
It's 1967, and rock music is about
to undergo a revolution,
although you wouldn't have
known it from the charts.
But then, BMI signed a band that
would change British musical landscape,
# Arnold Layne...
their name was Pink Floyd.
# ...had a strange hobby
# Collecting clothes
# Moonshine washing line
# They suit him fine
Arnold Layne, the band's first single,
was the story of an underwear
stealing transvestite,
not an obvious subject
for immediate chart success.
# ...a tall mirror
If you look, certainly, at the headlines
around at the time,
they were saying the "Pinky Kinkies"
and there was...
talk of whether BBC was gonna
ban it and all this stuff.
So I guess it's part and parcel,
really, of that sense that
Pink Floyd was all gleefully
pushing the envelope a little bit.
# Oh, Arnold Layne
# It's not the same...
Pink Floyd consisted of Roger Waters,
Richard Wright, Nick Mason,
and their maverick song-writer,
Syd Barrett,
an art school student
from Cambridge.
# Why can't you see?
No one in those days would have
written a song like that except for Syd.
I suppose that should've given us
an indication, this...
this guy's brain is rather
different to ours.
Syd and the band defined
a new kind of rock,
psychedelic, mind-expanding.
This was rock meets
the Mad Hatter's tea party.
I was passionately in love with the
writing of Syd Barrett, from Pink Floyd.
There was something slightly
not-quite-with-us about Syd
that really appealed to me strongly.
There was a Peter Pan quality about him.
Pink Floyd's second single,
"See Emily Play",
allegedly told the story
of young aristocrat
known as the psychedelic schoolgirl.
# Emily tries but misunderstands
# She often inclined to borrow
somebody's dreams till tomorrow
# There is no other day
# Let's try it another way
# You'll lose your mind and play
# Free games for may
# See Emily play
It had 'hit' written all over it.
Suddenly it took the band from being
a sort of underground band
and turned them into a 'top of the pops'
pop phenomenon.
And that meant that there was
an awful lot of idiot questions,
and an awful lot of pressure
on Syd to do interviews.
Why has it all got to be
so terribly loud? I just can't bear it.
I happen to have grown up in
the String Quartet, which is a bit softer,
so, why has it got to be so loud?
Well, I don't guess it has to be
but that's just the way we like it.
# See Emily play
"See Emily Play" was a top ten hit,
and Syd and the Floyd
became household names.
But Syd didn't want to be
a household name.
I think by the time we got on
"Top of the Pops" Syd was already...
struggling with the whole concept
of being a commercial rock musician
rather than being an artist.
What Syd wanted was a return to
the band's early experimental days,
when he created musical happenings.
Syd was responsible for
"Interstellar Overdrive"
which was improvised, lengthy,
no lyrics, atmospheric,
and actually ran through a whole
series of musical ideas in one piece.
"Interstellar Overdrive" became
the centerpiece of the band's live show,
it lasted anything
from 10 to 30 minutes.
It's built like a piece
of experimental music.
These four musicians, even the drummer,
really are just exploring and seeing
what they could do.
So it's rock music,
but it's not rock music
really as it'd been understood
as rock music prior to that point.
There are analogies
you can draw between that
and what the Velvet Underground
were doing at that point in New York.
The Velvet Underground were
testing the limits of rock
in a way no other band
had ever dared.
# White light, White light
goin' messin' up my mind
# White light, and don't you know
its gonna make me go blind
# White heat, aww white heat
it tickle me down to my toes
# White light, Ooo have mercy
while I'll have it goodness knows
# White light, White light
goin' messin' up my brain
# White light, Aww white light
its gonna drive me insane
# White heat, Aww white heat
it tickle me down to my toes
# White light, Aww white light
I said now goodness knows, do it
The Velvets were formed by singer
and songwriter Lou Reed,
guitarist Sterling Morrison,
drummer Maureen "Moe" Tucker,
and British viola player, John Cale.
We put three-chord rock
into one-chord rock, you know,
we just had a drone
through everything.
And one of the things that the
drone did for a lot of the songs is that
it created a tapestry for the ideas
we were very insistent on, breaking rules.
The Velvet Underground used
New York's dark underbelly,
with its mean streets and drug deals,
as raw material for their songs.
This was unheard of
in rock music at the time.
# I'm waiting for my man
# Twenty-six dollars in my hand
# Up to Lexington, 125
# Feel sick and dirty,
more dead than alive
# I'm waiting for my man
There was a big deal about
what we were writing about
but in novels it would be a big nothing.
It was just really absurd.
The godfather of American pop-art,
Andy Warhol, was intrigued,
and went to see the band at
the aptly named, "Café Bizarre".
# Oh pardon me sir,
it's the furthest from my mind
He liked what he saw
and invited the Velvets to hang out
and rehearse at the Factory,
his Manhattan studio.
He also decided to become
the band's manager.
We're sponsoring a new band,
it's called the Velvet Underground.
Well, since I don’t really
believe in painting anymore
I thought it would
be a nice way
of combining music and
art and films all together.
And the whole thing is being
auditioned tomorrow at 9:00.
And if it works out it might
be very glamorous.
# First thing you learn is
you always gotta wait
The audition was provocatively
held at the annual dinner
of the New York Society
for Clinical Psychiatry,
at the swish, little Monaco Hotel.
Warhol had been asked
to give a lecture,
but instead, decided to give
the Velvet's announcing.
He brought everybody from
the Factory down, including us.
But I don't remember whether we played
or people just run around
interviewing psychiatrists.
One commentator described
the night as "shock treatment"
administered by the Velvets to
an increasingly nervous group of shrinks.
# I'm waiting for my man
With Warhol now in charge of the asylum
he landed the Velvets a recording deal,
but insisted on adding his new discovery,
German singer, Nico, to the line-up.
# And what costume shall
the poor girl wear
# To all tomorrow's parties
Andy made everything possible.
I don't know if I ever would've been able
to keep writing what I was writing
if it hadn't been for Andy and his...
umbrella of protection
and his approval.
When we got a record contract,
which was really based on him,
I could write whatever
and they wouldn't change it
or try to change it
because Andy was there.
There was no problem with the songs
or what they were about
because the people of the record
company couldn't stand the music,
they wouldn't listen to
the records in the first place.
And in the studio, the engineers
didn't like it, they would leave.
And say, "I don't have to listen
to this shit."
In late 1966, the band recorded
their debut album...
in just two days.
During the Velvet's
stay at the Factory,
the band became part of Warhol's
traveling circus
known as
"The Exploding Plastic Inevitable".
Warhol came up with the idea of
projecting images over the band.
There were four projectors,
all projecting different kind of film.
There were slides.
There was the mirror ball overhead
on which was shone several
different coloured pin lights.
So, it was swimming in stars and
the one wall was covered
with multiple images.
And then Nico would stand in white
in the middle of this darkened stage.
The Velvet Underground performances
became the most
elaborate multi-media show
rock music had ever experienced.
It seemed the very natural thing to do
even though it hadn't been done before.
Lou and Andy wanted
to break the boundaries
but they didn't know exactly where
that was gonna take them so
it took on the form of experimentation.
By creating a total environment,
music, art and film, all combined,
the Velvets and Andy Warhol
were to sow the seeds
for the next generation of rock.
It was that... The Velvet Underground
sold very few records
but just about everybody
who bought one of their records
later went out
and started a band.
Pink Floyd's manager, Peter Jenner, had
heard a tape of the Velvet Underground,
and saw his band as
the British equivalent.
# Lime and limpid green, a second scene
# A fight between
the blue you once knew.
# Floating down, the sound resounds
# Around the icy waters underground.
Like the Velvet Underground, the Floyd
were about breaking the barriers
between art and music.
Lights were very important
and encouraged the idea of
what they were doing as being art,
rather than just being a rock band.
# Neptune, Titan, Stars can frighten.
Like the Velvet Underground
before them,
Pink Floyd understood how manipulating
their stage presentation
could add to the power of their music.
Why the Floyd became
so big so quickly?
It was because what they were doing
was culturally and musically
different and radical.
In a context of a socially radical
and political time.
And when the lights and
music of Pink Floyd
were combined with the drug
of the moment, LSD,
rock entered its psychedelic phase.
But LSD was also to be the undoing
of lead singer, Syd Barrett,
who indulged in ever
increasing quantities
to cope with the band's success.
As the drugs took over,
Syd wrote about his world
falling apart around him.
# It's awfully considerate of you
to think of me here
# And I'm much obliged to you
for making it clear
# That I'm not here.
'Jugband Blues' is Syd Barrett's
kind of last word
within the context of the Floyd.
It's really the sound of
someone going mad.
The absence of structure and the idea
of pushing the envelope
by that point
has turned absolutely crazy.
So it's about being
disjointed from oneself.
# ...instead dressed in red
# And I'm wondering who
could be writing this song.
It's so sort of disjointed and chaotic.
And on a whim, in Jugband Blues,
what sounds like a salvation army band
suddenly sort of intrudes
on the whole thing.
If you want to understand
what it's like loosing your mind,
'Jugband Blues' isn't a bad
place to start.
Syd's days in the Floyd were numbered.
His erratic behaviour
led to a group decision
to employ one of his old friends,
David Gilmour,
to fill in on Syd's off days.
It was awkward, I mean,
initially it was me adding on.
I became a fifth member,
initially, for a few weeks.
So that part wasn't too bad.
I'd just come along, play a bit,
sing a bit and uh...
Syd would sit there and
play a bit and sing a bit too.
He wasn't really functioning
particularly well.
# And what exactly is a dream
# And what exactly is a joke.
On the 15th of January, 1968,
Syd Barrett played the last concert
of his life with the Pink Floyd,
on a faded pier in Hastings,
on the South coast.
But although Syd was gone,
he had kick-started a revolution
that would take rock music
to a different planet.
# Let's try it another way.
# Ground Control to Major Tom
A planet inhabited by a struggling
young singer called David Bowie,
who'd been watching every move
Syd had made.
Syd Barrett probably started
an idea in David's head.
He definitely found not only the music
inspirational but...
what actually had happened to Syd.
The way he walked away from the Pink Floyd,
the way he went slowly mad
and retreated into the background.
For sure, it was one
of his great, great inspirations.
# This is Ground Control to Major Tom
# You've really made the grade
But Syd Barrett was only part
of the mix for David Bowie,
as he morphed from one character
to another in his search for success.
I wanted to make a mark,
and I didn't know quite how to do it.
And it took me all the 60s to try
every thing that I could think of,
in terms of theater and arts and music.
# Ground Control to Major Tom
# Your circuit's dead,
there's something wrong
# Can you hear me, Major Tom?
# Can you hear...
# am I floating round my tin can
Although Bowie had a novelty hit
with "Space Oddity",
real success was still proving elusive.
But then, in 1971,
he went to New York
and met a band that would
provide him with a new direction.
The Velvet Underground became
very important to me
as I felt there was
something so expressive
about that sense of otherness.
And the Underground were, I thought,
the most incredible sound.
There was this sort of mixture
between rock and avant-garde.
And the combination was so brutal.
Inspired by the Velvet Underground,
Bowie's first move in the new decade
was to create a rock band
with a difference.
He called it "The Hype",
and it was to be the turning point
in Bowie's career.
We played a gig at the Roundhouse
in London.
We decided, let's do something different,
let's not just go out
wearing plaid shirts.
Let's not go up on the stage
wearing jeans,
and having long hair and, you know,
doing what everyone else was doing.
# I'm waiting for the man
Hype was much more rock oriented
than anything that he'd done before.
And clearly in the songs,
and perhaps in the stage presentation,
was influenced by what he'd heard
of the Velvet Underground.
Most obviously, one of the songs that
Hype covered was "Waiting for the Man".
# I'm waiting for the man
But even a Velvet's number
couldn't rescue the evening for
Bowie and his band of rockers.
# ...what you doin' uptown?
We weren't even booed.
It was really just the most
depressive night of our lives.
'Cause we thought we were kind of,
you know, smart,
but nobody even looked
at the stage.
So it was all to no avail, but that was
a wonderful show inasmuch that
then I knew that theater
was for me after that.
I think that this was a very pivotal
evening for David.
It is my theory that this is
the night it all started.
Hype was definitely the precursor to
Ziggy Stardust and the Spiders from Mars.
# Ziggy played guitar,
# jammin' good with Weird and Gilly,
# The spiders from Mars...
David Bowie's most iconic creation
to date was called Ziggy Stardust.
The character of
Ziggy Stardust himself,
this messianic, space-age,
plastic rock 'n roller
is obviously created out of many,
many different bits and pieces,
and there are all sorts
of different people,
characters real and fictional in there.
But Syd is certainly in there.
This glamourous, British,
slightly unstable rock 'n roller.
And also, of course, Lou Reed and
the Velvet are definitely in there
in terms of this very cool,
street-wise rock.
# ...and snow white tan
# So where were the spiders
while the fly tried to break our balls
# Just a beer light to guide us
# So we bitched about his fans
and should we crush his sweet hands?
To immortalise his new creation,
Bowie created a
concept album for Ziggy.
The album began with an apocalyptic
vision of the future.
The slow, ominous drumbeat
at the beginning of "Five years"
is one of the most iconic album
opening moments in rock history.
And Five Years is a fascinating song.
On the surface of it, of course,
is the story of society
and interaction breaking down
as the news comes
that the Earth is going to die
in five years time.
# Pushing thru the market square,
so many mothers crying
# News had just come over,
we had five years left to sigh in
But on another level, you almost
get the impression of Bowie/Ziggy
calling together his disciples.
All these dispossessed, lonely,
wounded characters.
All being drawn in towards Bowie.
# ...I think she would have killed them
# A soldier with a broken arm,
fixed his stare to the wheels of a Cadillac
# A cop knelt and kissed
the feet of a priest,
# and a queer threw up
at the sight of that
With Ziggy, Bowie now had a vision
which he hoped would give him
the success he so craved.
But there was still one thing missing.
# Smiling and waving
and looking so fine...
We handed 'Ziggy Stardust' in and
RCA didn't hear a single on it so...
they asked us to go back in and
David came up with the song 'Starman',
and they thought it was great.
# Didnt know what time it was
the lights were low oh how
# I leaned back on my radio oh oh
# Some cat was layin down some
rock 'n roll lotta soul, he said
# Then the loud sound did seem to fade
# Came back like a slow voice
on a wave of phase
# That weren't no d.j.
that was hazy cosmic jive
'Starman' made Bowie... a star.
# There's a starman waiting in the sky
# He'd like to come and meet us
# But he thinks he'd blow our minds
# There's a starman waiting in the sky
# He's told us not to blow it
# Cause he knows its all worthwhile
# He told me: Let the children...
Ziggymania hit Britain.
The tear-shaped mascara
and a little lippy
had put the glamour into rock.
# There's a starman waiting in the sky
# He'd like to come and meet us
# But he thinks he'd blow our minds
And while Bowie had found his way,
Pink Floyd were still experimenting,
searching for a sound that would
recapture some of the success
Barrett had brought the band.
We were looking for direction
and we didn't want to compromise
the art that we were making.
We wanted to do longer pieces
that were connected by ideas,
and that's what we were looking at.
It's just on the first note.
- Say that again.
- I went out in one place, didn't I?
With the band's album 'Meddle'
and its 23-minute
extended track, 'Echoes',
Pink Floyd found their
signature sound.
I was in the studio, playing the piano,
and, maybe it was me,
maybe it was Roger,
maybe it was Dave, we said,
"I wonder what the piano would
sound like going through a 'Leslie'."
- Rick started plonking on the piano...
- "Wow! What a great noise."
And they had a tape running
and that is the beginning of 'Echoes'.
It's Rick just sitting there,
mucking about...
The grand design of 'Echoes'
suited its performance in the dramatic
Roman amphitheater at Pompey.
# Overhead the albatross
hangs motionless upon the air
# And deep beneath the rolling waves
# In labyrinths of coral caves
# The echo of a distant time
# Comes willowing across the sand
# And everything is green and submarine
Pink Floyd, no longer improvising,
created a cinematic epic into which
the listener could escape.
# And no-one knows the wheres or whys
# But something stirs and something tries
# And starts to climb towards the light
The audience feels that they're going
on some sort of... a journey with us.
I hesitate to use the word "trip".
'Cause the other sort of trip
wasn't where we were at.
Having found musical direction
with the album 'Meddle',
Pink Floyd's next project would take
them into a new level entirely.
'Dark Side' develops what 'Echoes' did,
which is taking one
very long piece of music
and seeing what you can do with it.
It just so happens that in the course of
that long piece of music on 'Dark Side',
you get a lot of great
and memorable songs...
which stand on their own.
# Ticking away the moments
that make up a dull day
# You fritter and waste
the hours in an off hand way
# Kicking around...
'Dark Side of the Moon', with its lyrics
about the pressure of modern life,
struck a chord with almost
everyone who heard it.
It became a rock classic.
# Tired of lying in the sunshine...
It's really about how
the machinery of living
comes between us and our potential
to develop as human beings, and grow.
It's about the influences that prevent
our individual development.
Although individual tracks
explored money, war and time,
the overriding theme of the album
was insanity.
Lunacy is at the heart
of that album.
But it would be hard to make
a whole album
about the many pressures in one's
life that can drive one to lunacy...
at that point, without Syd
being in there, somewhere.
# The lunatic is on the grass
# Remembering games
and daisy chains and laughs
# Got to keep the loonies on the path
# The lunatic is in the hall
It's very easy to sing those lyrics
with passion, standing on stage,
and it's very easy to understand why
all those lips moving in unison out there
could totally understand
what it was expressing.
'Dark Side of the Moon' shifted millions
and billions of units worldwide.
Pink Floyd, once the darlings
of the underground,
were now mainstream rock superstars.
# And if the dam breaks
open many years too soon
# And if there is no room upon the hill
# And if your head explodes
with dark forebodings too
# I'll see on the dark side of the moon
When we finished the album we had
no idea how successful it'd be,
but I think we all said,
"That's good.
"We've finally done something
that we can all be very proud of."
To complement the album, Floyd moved
from their early light shows,
into large scale theatrical spectacles.
# Money get away
From 'Dark Side' on,
I wanted to get away from the visual
aspects of the show being abstract,
and not illustrate what the songs
were actually about.
And so when we started
using films,
it was in order to sort of
drive home the message.
# ...with both hands and make a stash
# new car, caviar, four star daydream
# think I'll buy me a football team
'Dark Side' was really the beginning
of proper staging.
A big screen behind us,
in a circular screen,
which was considered to be
wonderfully extraordinary,
we had film running
on the screen behind,
and every now and again, there'd be
a few explosions, or fireworks,
and in particular the crashing plane.
Anything that could be done to add
something to the music.
But spectacular as the Floyd shows were,
the band seemed dwarfed
by their theatrics.
Not something that could
be said of David Bowie.
On the 17th and 18th of August, 1972,
Bowie embarked
on two of the most ambitious
and influential shows in rock history
at the Rainbow Theater
in London's Finsbury Park.
To help him, he requested the assistance
of his old mime teacher from the 60s.
I got a call from David Bowie's wife.
She explained if I would
like to go to London to stage
a show which was to be called
'Ziggy Stardust'.
Which for me was quite shocking.
It wasn't the David Bowie that I knew,
it was a very rock 'n roll David Bowie.
# ...we don't talk much,
we just ball and play
# But then we move
like tigers on vaseline
# You know the bitter comes out
better on a stolen guitar
# You're the blessed,
we're the spiders from Mars
# So come on, come on,
we've really got a good thing going
# Well come on, well come on,
if you think we're gonna make it
# You better hang on to yourself
Bowie wanted the Rainbow concert
to be the ultimate expression
of everything he'd learned so far.
David had absorbed so much.
He just took so much from
the theatrical elements
many of which I had introduced him to.
The Rainbow shows,
in a sense, were
a synthesis of everything that Bowie
had worked on up until that point.
Along with the music itself,
there was mime, dance, choreography,
there were projections...
# ...five years, stuck on my eyes
# Five years, what a surprise
When I saw that Rainbow show,
it was as if a giant window
had opened in front of me,
and it was like, "Yes! This is what
the future looks like."
No beards, no flairs*,
no grubby grandad vests.
By comparison with the standard issue
rock 'n roll show at the time,
this was amazing.
# Five years, that's all we've got
David's a very smart man, and he's
bringing in things from everywhere.
If there was music on Pluto
and he heard it,
I'm sure he'd work it
into his next record.
By special request from Bowie himself,
that night's entertainment also
included rock's newest sensation,
# I tried but I could not find a way
# Looking back all I did was look away
I think that was such a good pairing,
with us and him.
And we were so different musically
that there was no conflict
of interest going on.
And he was very vocally appreciative
and supportive of all we were doing.
# She's the sweetest queen
I've ever seen...
Roxy Music and Bowie were
the perfect combination.
Bowie had turned inventiveness
into an art form
and Roxy had just released one of
the most innovative singles ever produced.
A single that was to prove
a much needed antidote
to gray 1970s Britain.
When we went in to record
'Virginia Plane', I felt I was...
the rhythm guitarist in
the Velvet Underground, or something.
The whole thing starts with...
some 'fuzz' thing with the section
...also on the base,
but then when I come in
with the rhythm guitar...
# Make me a deal and make it straight
# All signed and sealed, I'll take it
# To Robert E. Lee I'll show it
# I hope and pray he don't blow it 'cause
# We've been around a long time
just try try try tryin' to
# Make the big time...
That song itself is a kind
of rare collage of ideas of...
almost free association of things
which appealed to me...
# Take me on a roller coaster
# Take me for an airplane ride
# Take me for a six days
wonder but don´t you
# Don't you throw my pride aside besides
# What's real and make believe
# Baby Jane's in Acapulco
we are flyin' down to Rio
Roxy were radical in just about
every department.
The idea that a group like
Roxy Music could arrive,
put out something like 'Virginia Plain'
for their first single,
and have a hit with it,
that is an achievement which
definitely rebounds to
the great honour of all concerned.
# Far beyond the pale horizon
# Some place near the desert strand
# Where my Studebaker takes me
# That's where I'll make
my stand but wait
# Can't you see that holzer mane?
# What's her name Virginia Plain
Roxy Music were the quintessential
art school band.
Bryan Ferry, the group's singer
and songwriter,
had studied at Newcastle with
the English equivalent of Andy Warhol,
artist Richard Hamilton.
He had a reputation amongst
progressive thinking art students
of being the absolute guru
of modern "cool".
What you tended to learn from Richard
was not how to be an artist,
but how to think about art.
Ferry was the latest in a long
line of art students turned musicians.
All the artistic energy that I was
previously directing into paintings,
it was all now... all of that impulse
was going into music, into the songs.
# I would wak a thousand miles...
To showcase his ideas, Ferry formed
a band of likeminded individuals,
including Brian Eno,
Phil Manzanera and Andy Mackay.
As a collective, they were focused
on pushing the boundaries
of what a rock band could be.
We did have an artistic vision.
We all knew about the history
of 20th century art and performance,
and we somehow flattered ourselves
that it could be got into rock music.
# Blue suns and grey lagoons
# Silver starfish with honeymoons
# All these and more to choose
Rock 'n roll was about what you play
and how you look...
the whole thing needed a bit
more theater and a bit more fun.
And that's uh... that's what we did,
set out to do that.
#... strange goodbyes
In the summer of 1972,
the band released their first album,
adorned with a glamourous
50s style pin-up.
Widely regarded as one of
the greatest rock debuts ever made,
it was simply called 'Roxy Music'.
It was a musical collage of sounds
and moods from the past into the future.
Roxy Music were bringing in
all the tone colours
of Andy Mackay's saxophone and oboe.
I mean, when did you last
hear an oboe in a rock band?
And Eno with his synthesizers,
they seemed both retro
and futurist.
This is a 1950s revival show
taking place in the year 2020.
# You've got me girl on the run
around run around
# You've got me all around town
On 'Ladytron', that's probably the best
example of Eno treating my guitar.
If I just play it straight
on this guitar is...
which is one of the beginning bits.
But once it went through his synthesizers
it sounded like something that came
from the planet Zorg, or something.
# Lady if you want to find a lover
# Then you look no further
# For I'm gonna be your only
# Searching at the start of the season
# And my only reason
# Is that I'll get to you
One of the reasons why Roxy
became so popular,
not just with kind of serious,
kind of "muso" types,
but with real, high street teen
stormtroopers of glam,
was because they offered this imaginary
world and invited you to join it.
# I´ll find some way of connection...
Roxy Music, with the way they looked,
the way they dressed,
and the physicality they brought
to their performance,
that was all the theater you needed.
But there was a band out there,
led by Peter Gabriel,
who thought they could push
rock theater just one step further
when they mixed the sinister world
of English suburbia,
with a dash of Syd Barrett whimsy,
and a dive into the dressing odd-box.
Peter would put on a hat for
"I Know What I Like",
and would go around the stage
pretending to be the lawn mower.
He always did it in such a way
where people would say,
"What's he doing?
Is that really a lawn mower?"
You know, he was never literal,
which was a good thing.
# There's always been Ethel:
# "Jacob, wake up! you've got
to tidy your room now."
# And then Mister Lewis:
# "Isn't it time that he was
out on his own?"
# Over the garden wall,
two little lovebirds - cuckoo to you!
# Keep them mowing blades sharp...
# I know what I like,
and I like what I know
Where Genesis' music and
Gabriel's song writing
link up to the Syd Barrett tradition
is their use of imagery derived from
that cozy suburban English banality
gone seriously wrong.
The underlying strangeness
of English "normality".
Genesis were formed in an English
public school by Peter Gabriel,
Mike Rutherford and Tony Banks.
They were later joined
by the drummer, Phil Collins.
Their early days were marked by
a distinctly understated stage presence.
We were very boring... to look at.
That's the first thing.
That's why our albums never
had pictures on them.
And we were very quick to understand
that we looked like everybody else.
It felt I had this huge responsibility
of being the link between
what the band were trying to do
and what the audience wanted.
And I had to, somehow,
get the two to connect.
Gabriel, like Bowie and Floyd
before him,
knew he had to reinvent Genesis
to counter the image problem.
His band were in for a shock.
I remember he walked on stage,
and we were all kind of just,
you know, playing along...
And it's like...
"What the h--? What is that?"
And Peter Gabriel comes out
in a red dress and a fox's head.
You know, you kind of do
a double take, as if...
as if the next turn's come on
before you've finished.
"Comedians, come on! Comedians, come on!
We haven't finished here."
# I've been waiting here so long
So there was a deathly silence
when I walked out,
and I thought, "Oh, this is interesting.
I'll try some more of this."
There was a bloody argument
backstage afterwards, you know, like...
"We demand to be told this thing."
We'd liked to have known,
but he said, "If I'd told you, you'd said
"Don't. You can't!""
The next week, Peter was on
the front page of a makeup magazine,
so we thought,
we're onto something here.
With a new line in stage costumes,
Peter Gabriel and the band produced
their most successful album to date,
'Foxtrot',
which included
the haunting and surreal epic,
'Supper's Ready'.
'Supper's Ready' began with
these very atmospheric chords...
and it seemed a good place to put
this story of what had happened to me...
a strange and frightening experience.
I was trying to piece things together
lyrically that would tell a story,
or paint pictures.
# ...And it's hello babe with
your guardian eyes so blue.
# Hey, my baby don't you
know our love is true.
Nearly 23 minutes long,
'Supper's Ready' was one piece
made up of a number
of musical sections.
# A flower?
# If you go down to Willow Farm,
# to look for butterflies,
flutterbyes, gutterflies
# Open your eyes, it's full of surprise,
everyone lies
# like the focks on the rocks,
# and the musical box.
There were a lot of elements
of my childhood in 'Supper's Ready'.
'Bill and Ben' was the program that
I watched as a 3 or 4 year old,
and there was these flower-pot men,
and there was 'Weed' who
was this big, floral character.
It obviously sunk deep
into my subconscious.
# We've got everything,
we're growing everything,
# We've got some in
# We've got some out
# We've got some wild
things floating about.
# Everyone, we're changing everyone,
# you name them all,
# We've had them here,
# And the real stars are still to appear.
In terms of the theatrical tradition
in British rock, I think...
the other end of the spectrum from
what Bowie and Roxy Music were doing
was Genesis.
Certainly in terms of
the costumes he wore,
he took the dressing-up
tendency of British rock
several stages beyond even
where Bowie had gone.
By comparison with some of the stuff
Gabriel wore on stage,
Bowie was dressed for a Sunday
afternoon at the pub.
# Momma I want you now.
Rock theater was becoming
ever more elaborate,
attracting ever larger audiences
in ever bigger venues.
But this came at a price,
spectacle was replacing intimacy.
A dilemma felt even by
the kings of rock theater, Pink Floyd.
I famously became very disgruntled
on the road with huge audiences.
The audience was just
growing exponentially
and I did feel it all got
a bit out of control.
That we were being
overcome by commerce.
I found myself increasingly
upset by people in the audience
just going, "Argh!",
for two hours rather than
listening to what we were doing.
Roger Waters' solution
to the problem was radical.
He would send up the whole process
while ironically still
providing the rock world
with one of the most ambitious
shows in its history.
The idea formed in my mind of...
of doing a show where
we would actually
physically build a wall across
the front of the stage
to express my feeling of alienation
from that part of the audience.
# We don't need no education
# We don't need no thought control
Released in 1979, 'The Wall' double
album became a huge success,
and delivered an unexpected
hit single for the band.
# Hey! Teachers! Leave them kids alone!
But not everyone was convinced
by Roger Waters' stage concept.
# All in all you're just
another brick in the wall.
I thought the idea was crazy,
I have to say.
I loved having an audience.
I thought, it's a bit illogical this.
If you're going to build a wall between
the audience why bother to turn up.
Why do it anyway?
# No! don’t think I’ll need
anything at all
The building of the wall went on
throughout the whole first half.
And we were gradually
becoming obscured.
And at the end of the first half
it'd be 'Goodbye Cruel World'...
and then the last brick
would go on.
# Goodbye, cruel world,
I'm leaving you today
# Goodbye, goodbye, goodbye
# Goodbye, all you people,
there's nothing you can say
# To make me change my mind
# Goodbye
One of the most iconic moments
of the performance
showed off one of Pink Floyd's
best loved songs,
sung by David Gilmour
from the dizzying heights
on the top of the wall.
# Come on, it's time to go
# There is no pain you are receding
# A distant ship, smoke on the horizon.
# You are only coming through in waves.
# Your lips move but I can't hear
what you're saying.
# I have become comfortably numb.
As the show progressed,
the wall became a vast cinema screen
showing satirical animations created
by caricaturist, Gerald Scarfe.
The Floyd were pushing the boundary and
I loved the theatricality of their work.
Something of that excitement
got into me and made want to
illustrate and enhance them visually.
Taking yourself seriously and trying
to make some sort of grand spectacle
had never got as ambitious
or overblown,
depending on which way
you look at it,
as that before, but certainly in terms
of a kind of touring show
that you can sit in
an auditorium and see,
'The Wall' was almost
preposterously ambitious.
When the show came to its end,
the wall came crashing down,
only to be rebuilt again the next night.
It was the ultimate theatrical show
that Floyd could put on, that's for sure.
Where could you go from there?
The cost of the performance
was prohibitive,
and the show was seen
in just four cities,
and then only in massive arenas.
Many questioned whether rock
theatricality had gone a brick to far.
With 'The Wall', the great irony
was that part of the inspiration
was Roger Waters' increasing distaste
for the way that stadium performance
was isolating the band
from the audience.
# When we grew up and went to school,
# There were certain teachers who
# Would hurt the children
anyway they could
So in order to dramatise this,
he created this huge theatrical spectacle
which effectively alienated
the band from the audience
more effectively than anything
staged by any band beforehand, ever.
# But in the town it was well known
# When they got home at night...
Rock music and performance
was now light-years away
from the light shows pioneered
by the Velvet Underground.
It had picked up glamour and style
from David Bowie and Roxy Music,
gone surreal with Genesis,
and reached epic scale
with the Pink Floyd shows.
The ideas and innovations
begun in the 1960s and 70s
created a whole new dimension
for popular music.
Its pioneers were
the godfathers of rock.
Next week on 'Seven Ages of Rock'
all bets are off
as "punk" joins the party.
To find out more about
'The Seven Ages of Rock'
and see some extra stories
featuring artists in the series,
go to "bbc.co.uk/sevenages".
Transcription and
synchronization by Fry.