Seattle, Washington, in the early 90s
the music capital of the world.
# With the lights out
its less dangerous
Home to grunge, teen spirit and
the kings of alternative rock, Nirvana.
# I feel stupid and contagious
# Here we are now
# Entertain us
# A mulatto
The band that brought the sound
of the American underground
to a mass audience.
The moment they took the stage
it was like hysteria, like Beatlemania.
People crying and screaming and...
The hair at the back
of my neck went up.
In Kurt Cobain, Nirvana
had an artist of rare power
who gave a voice
to a generation.
Every time he touched the guitar
it was beautiful.
Every single time.
He was amazing. He really had something
that I've never seen in anyone else.
Nirvana's success had put
Seattle on the map.
Now, even the band that had laid
the foundations of alternative rock
descended on the city,
R.E.M.
Hi, this is Mike Milles of REM
and you're listening to KC...
# That's me in the corner
# That's me in the spotlight
losing my religion
When REM and Nirvana
came together
it would lead to the great
might-have-beens of rock history.
I said to Kurt, "You wanna play with us?"
He was, "Man! I'd like nothing more."
All I could think about was
what a freaking tour that would be
to have us and them on the same stage,
on the same night.
But the chances of the two biggest
rock bands on the planet
sharing a stage was slim,
as Kurt Cobain plunged into a spiral
of depression and drug-addiction
that no one could save him from.
I created a project that he had
to flight to Georgia to work with me on,
in an attempt to pull him out of
headspace that he was in in Seattle,
in his house all alone,
but it didn't work.
Sadly.
This is the story of the age
of alternative rock,
when a handful of bands restored
authenticity, meaning
and passion to the music.
And the lasting legacy of the artist
who continues to cast a powerful shadow
over the whole of rock.
Kurt Cobain is the last great rock star,
and I think that's one reason there still
remains so much fascination with him.
An electrician arrived at Kurt Cobain's
luxurious home early in the morning.
... we need to notify the family.
Apparently it was a suicide
at the age of 27.
In the 1980s,
Ronald Reagan's presidency
served up an American dream
of growth and prosperity
for some.
It's morning again in America.
Today more men and women
will go to work
than ever before
in our country's history.
Now you have
everything you wanted.
Including you?
Unless you voted for Reagan,
you didn't have
a great time under Reagan.
It's morning in America for people
who contributed to that campaign,
who shared those ideals.
It wasn't morning in America
for anyone else.
It was like the sun
had just set.
# It's the end of the world
as we know it
# and I feel fine
There was an immense frustration
in the country that was palpable
and we certainly shared it
as political activists, as people who...
felt like the very idea of America
was being pulled out from under us.
# The other night I dreamt of knives,
# continental drift divide.
Mountains sit in a line
# Leonard Bernstein...
Reaganomics delivered shock
treatment to the American economy,
sweeping aside the idealism
values of the 1960s.
Those unable or unwilling to conform
were in for a rough ride.
We got no prospects,
you know, what are you gonna do,
work at McDonalds? Deliver papers?
You feel like not only
are you in a minority
but you feel like you're in
a minority nobody gives a shit about.
# Well a person can work up
a mean mean thirst
# After a hard day
of nothin' much at all
In the depressed logging town
of Aberdeen in Washington St.,
Kurt Cobain was part
of that minority.
A high-school dropout
from a broken home,
Kurt entered a downsize world
of dead end jobs in 1985.
He ended up getting a job
back at the high school
that he had dropped out of.
He was the janitor.
So you can imagine the shame
that he must have felt of
coming in the halls and seeing kids that
were his classmates just months before,
and they're going off to college
and what he's doing is mopping the floor.
Kurt's experience was not unique.
He was part of "Generation X",
children who felt alienated
and excluded from
conventional society,
who would never enjoy the prospects
their baby-boomer parents
had taken for granted.
Kurt would find a soulmate in Aberdeen,
who shared a similar
background and outlook,
Krist Novoselic.
A lot of it had to do with our
personal situations, family things and
maybe ideals and promises broken.
It boiled down to alienation
and recognising
we'd look at the mainstream culture
and see that it didn't
have a lot to offer us.
The real lives and emotions
of America's alienated youth
weren't reflected
in the studio polished rock
that filled mainstream radio
and MTV.
# But what I need to make me tight are
# Girls, Girls, Girls
# Long legs and burgundy lips
I was not getting what I needed
from Ted Nugent.
I was a young guy going
to a school I hated,
like a lot of young men,
you hate the school, the teachers,
you want to burn the place
to the ground,
and you want something or
someone to represent that for you.
Van Halen sang about girls...
Fine!
But there wasn't the "white riot,
I wanna riot" thing happening.
And there was no sense
of dislocation in that music,
where I... I'm out.
I hate all of y'all.
Henry Rollins' search for an alternative
would lead him to join a band
whose fearsome reputation
would thrill and inspire
Kurt Cobain and Krist Novoselic,
Black Flag.
I got a six-pack,
and nothing to do.
I actually went to see Black Flag play
in Walla Walla, Washington, in 1984.
And they had this idea that
they were gonna tour the hinterlands
and bring the message to the people.
And it was amazing.
# Thirty-five dollars
and a six pack to my name
# Six-pack!
# Spent the rest on beer
so who's to blame
# Six-pack!
Black Flag played an adrenaline charged
brand of punk known as 'hard core',
a sound that captured the frustration
and rage experienced by many
growing up in Reagan's America.
# I got a six pack in me alright!
It was this post-punk,
letting out that angst,
and just that very honest
fury of youth
and all that confusion and pain
into this very short bursts of music.
# Now I got a six so I'll never run out
# Six pack!
Some people are gonna listen to
Black Flag and they're gonna love it,
and some people...
it's gonna scare them.
Black Flag earned the reputation
of staging shows
which frequently descended
into violence.
# Six pack!
What do they know
about partying?
Or anything else?
He runs this place.
You'd set up to play in some town
and then here comes the mayor,
and a news team, and a reverend.
And here comes the Christians
protesting and lighting candles,
going like, "Oh my God! No!
Help our children!"
# I don't care what's inside
# We're not gonna kill you!
We're like four starving
vegetarians in a van,
so they're ready for
this fire-breathing beast,
and we're like, "Hi, we're Black Flag.
We hate everyone"
It's all right ma'm.
They've gone.
# Gimme, gimme, gimme
# I need some more
Finding somewhere to play
was a challenge for the bands
on the growing alternative scene.
Unable to fill cavernous
arenas and ballrooms,
they had to create their
own improvised circuit.
What Black Flag had to do
was basically
blaze their own trail,
and they cobbled together
this kind of underground
railroad of indie rock.
All across America, a whole generation
of alternative rock bands
from Black Flag to R.E.M
came of age in venues as eclectic
as the bands themselves.
There was a small circuit of
clubs, pizza parlors and gay bars
and tiny places around the country
that would open their doors
and have really shitty sound systems
and let these bands play.
There were times when Black Flag would
play on a Friday and R.E.M. on a Saturday
and the next week we'd play the Friday
and they'd play the Saturday.
We were chasing each other for years.
And pretty soon there was a circuit.
And when there's a circuit
there's a scene.
And when there's a scene
there's a community.
And when there's a community then
you've got something really interesting.
That community united
a wide variety of bands
who shared the same independent spirit
and circumstances,
and a fierce determination
to make it on their own terms.
Touring bands in a van get by.
And what do you get in return?
300 hundred sweaty,
adoring fans a night,
and your freedom,
your musical freedom.
And maybe you missed some meals
or the cops came and
shut your show down,
but man, you weren't flipping burgers,
and you weren't filling slurpies.
And there was something
to be said for that.
Life on the road was an essential rite of
passage for all alternative rock bands.
But for R.E.M,
a band that had formed in 1980,
in the tiny university
town of Athens, Georgia,
it would also prove to be a springboard
to far greater success.
And it began with a song inspired
by a cold war radio station,
Radio Free Europe
calls on Presov.
# Calling all in transit,
calling all in transit
# Radio free Europe, radio...
'Radio Free Europe' instantly laid out
the R.E.M. blueprint.
Peter Buck chiming guitar chords,
Mike Mills and Bill Berry's
energetic rhythm section,
but it would be Michael Stipe's
enigmatic vocals and performances
that became the band's
early trademark.
# That this isn't country at all
I was just an incredibly shy person
and not terribly confident.
I had terrible acne and used my hair
to cover my face a lot.
I mumbled when I talked
and mumbled when I sang.
So all that combined into what I guess
came across as some modicum of charisma.
And people were very
taken by it.
# Calling all in transit,
calling all in transit
# Radio free Europe, radio...
Michael Stipe's mystique helped make
'Radio Free Europe' a critical hit,
as the new breed of bands began
to receive airplay
on another alternative network,
'Call It Radio'.
# Read about your band
in some local page
# Didn't mention your name,
didn't mention your name
It was that separate world of what
is now called alternative rock,
which at the time was only
called college rock
because the only place you heard it
on the radio was on college stations,
it's the classic Replacements' song
'Left of the Dial'.
# ...in a long, long while
# I'll try to find you
# Left of the dial
It's a song about where
you tuned manually,
you turned the little knob
to the left of the dial,
to the 88.9s and the 90.1s,
all the stuff that was below
the commercial band.
You had to look for it,
and people who really wanted
something more out of music,
who wanted more out of life,
something more out of their guitars,
that's where you went.
As more and more people
turned to the left of the dial
they discovered that even fast
and furious alternative rock bands,
such as Hüsker Dü were, like R.E.M.,
embracing melody and harmony.
# Going out each day to score
# She was no whore but for me
# Celebrating every day
# The way she thought it should be
# And I don't know what to do
When Hüsker Dü started
introducing melody
that introduced a whole
new audience of people.
It wasn't kind of the thuggish,
thick-necked guys
who just wanted to go to a show
and bash into each other.
You started to get people
with glasses and girls.
# For what she believed
# And I don't know what to do
# Now that pink has turned to blue
Major labels homed in on Hüsker Dü
and bands like The Replacements,
but R.E.M. were the anointed ones
of college radio,
and in 1987 they began work
on the album
that would launch them
into the mainstream,
'Document'.
We never intended to have
a commercial sound
because to us that was anathema.
Commercial sound equals death.
But we decided to make some records
that were more like what
we sounded like live.
And that's a very heavy guitar
dominated sound.
The band recruited Scot Litt,
the producer who had previously worked
with pop group Katrina and the Waves,
to help them craft a more
dynamic sound
that would yield
their first top ten hit.
# This one goes out
to the one I love
to the one I've left behind
# A simple prop to occupy my time
'The One I Love' was a dark love song
based around the arpegio guitar sound
Peter Buck created by plucking
rather than strumming the stings.
Peter Buck has the best right hand
in the business.
It is the essence of the R.E.M. sound,
certainly musically speaking,
because he decided
to *** the thrashing,
the full chord whatever thing
that everybody else was doing,
'cause that's the easy part.
The hard thing is working
with your right hand.
Michael Stipe delivered his most
clear and direct vocal yet,
even though the lyrics offered up
a dark and tangled tale
of manipulation and deceit.
# Fire!
'The one I love' is a song that
I didn't want to put on the record.
I thought it was too mean,
and too brutal and...
It was just a mean song.
As it turned out, I think
in recording, Scott and the band
recognised that
this might actually be
a song that could
get played on the radio.
So we turned the voice up a little.
It's a great song,
but the thing is, it's a sneaky one.
It's a dagger in the back.
It's not a love song, obviously,
for anyone who really
takes time to listen to it.
The song was punctuated
by dramatic cries of anguish.
# Fire!
Producer Scott Litt
emphasized the drama of the vocal
by adding a harmony from
drummer Bill Berry.
See? That kind of thing.
That's Bill doubled there.
Two of his voices
on one track.
That's how we would
thicken things up.
And then the great ending.
R.E.M.'s success showed
that alternative rock
was becoming a big business.
And it would change the lives
of the bands that had eked out
a humble living on the road
just a few years before.
I remember sitting with Michael Stipe
in his home in Athens, Georgia,
in his kitchen. He puts the phone down.
And he said, "What does
a gold record mean?"
And we had to call the office back
and go, "What does that mean?"
He goes, "It's half a million!"
"You sold half a million records?"
And I was there with Stipe
when that came over the wire.
And it was so cool that
neither of us knew.
And that was probably
the last time he didn't know, forever.
In Aberdeen,
gold records were distant dreams
for Kurt Cobain and Krist Novoselic,
but by 1988 they had
the makings of a band,
with Kurt on guitar and vocals,
Krist on base and
Chad Channing on drums.
Here we have your typical
American hard rock band
sitting up for a day's practice.
This goes into your guitar.
I found in Cobain's journals
at one point
a list of names he was considering,
and they included things like
Poo Poo Box, Spina Bifida,
Whisker Biscuit and a few others.
You just have to go back and say,
if this band had been named Poo Poo Box,
can you imagine them
overtaking the world
and selling 10 million
copies of their record?
Kurt finally settled on Nirvana.
But for an aspiring band
in Washington State
there was only one place to go,
Seattle.
The band drove up in a truck
that someone had borrowed
and I remember Novoselic telling me
there was actually a functioning
woodstove in the back.
It's like the 'Beverly Hillbillies',
essentially it's what they
looked like coming into Seattle.
Seattle's vibrant music scene
had spawned bands like Soundgarden
and Alice in Chains
with a dark, intense sound
inspired by 70s heavy metal,
and with lyrics full of alienation
and self-loathing... grunge.
And it had been unleashed
on the wider world by the band Mudhoney
with the song 'Touch me, I'm sick'.
# I'm a creep, yeah, I'm a jerk
# Come on
# Touch me, I'm sick
For the most part I just
stood back and let them go at it.
I enjoyed what they were doing.
I thought, "This is really noisy.
"Are you sure you want it
to be this noisy, guys?
"You really want the guitars
to sound this dirty? Mmm, Ok."
# ...girl - everything I got
'Grunge' means this kind of music
that's dripping with bits of garage rock,
and punk and metal and
it's just like hard, outrageous and
at the same time, just kind of like
living underneath a rock, in a way.
# If you don't come
# You'll die alone
Nirvana channeled the grunge sound
on their debut album, 'Bleach',
recorded for just 600$ on indie label
'Sub Pop', by Jack Endino.
But included one song the hinted
at Nirvana's crossover potential,
despite Kurt's reservations.
When it came the time to record
'About a girl',
which is the pop song in the record,
Kurt felt like he had
to sort of make an excuse for it.
He was a little uneasy about it.
He said, "Bear with me here, Jack.
"I've got this song,
it's kind of a pop song.
"I hope the Sub Pop guys like it
"and that they don't think
it's too commercial or something."
# I'm standing in your line
# I do, Hope you have the time
# I do, Pick a number too
# I do, Keep a date with you
# I'll take advantage while
# You hang me out to dry
# But I can't see you every night free
Kurt Cobain's concerns about the song
went to the heart
of the alternative rock dilemma,
the more popular it became
the more it risked loosing
its independence and integrity.
R.E.M. though, showed that
there might be a way forward.
They'd grown on their own terms
and Michael Stipe relished
the bigger stage,
but it came with a burden
of responsibility.
Yeah, I had become the voice
of a generation,
of political activism through
the Reagan years,
and I was suddenly expected
to have all the answers,
and to have encyclopedic, academic
knowledge on say, the greenhouse effect.
And I didn't realise what I had done,
what I was doing was speaking out
about things I was concerned
about as a person.
# I believe in watching you
# I believe in what you do
# I could turn you inside-out
R.E.M.'s 1989 'Green' Tour
had been exhilarating but exhausting.
After a decade on the road,
they'd earned the creative
freedom to do whatever they wanted.
Even if that meant laying down
their guitars.
We had been on tour from April 5th
of 1980, the first show that we ever did,
until the end of 1989.
We had not stopped touring
or recording and at the end
of the Green World Tour,
I think Bill Berry is the one
who said, I can't do this,
we need to take a break,
and so we took a long break.
Peter was, I think, afraid
of becoming a rock icon
so he put down the electric guitar,
he was sick of it,
and picked up a mandolin.
R.E.M.'s new sound would be
perfectly crystallised in a song
that was to become
their defining chart hit.
# Oh, life is bigger
# It's bigger than you
# And you are not me
# The lengths that I will go to
The success of 'Losing my religion'
owed much to a striking video
that put Michael Stipe
firmly in the spotlight.
# Oh no, I've said too much
# I haven't said enough
# I thought that I heard you laughing
Peter Buck plucked
the strings of the mandolin
in the R.E.M. arpegio style,
but he couldn't resist adding
a subtle chime of electric guitar.
That's a guitar called a 'Robin',
Peter used to call it his 'Robin'.
It's an electric guitar but
it's in the octave of the mandolin.
There's the mandolin.
And this doubling guitar
doesn't need to strum along really,
so we just...
just having downbeats arpegiated.
Scott Litt enhanced the lushness
of the sound with a string section.
Violins, violas...
Again the movement in the track.
# I think I thought I saw you try
# That was just a dream
# Try, cry, why try?
The video cemented R.E.M.
as MTV favourites,
even though the band hadn't been
convinced that the song would be a hit.
Why would anyone be surprised?
Its a 5'30'' song with a mandolin
as the lead instrument.
There's no chorus.
Why wouldn't that be a hit?
That should be a hit everywhere.
There's R.E.M. before and after
'Loosing my religion',
it was a huge, huge
international hit.
And I went from being a fairly
well known but fringe pop star
to being a full blown celebrity.
We'd like to especially
thank 'College Radio'
for supporting us all these years
and putting us here tonight.
And we'd like to thank the fans
from twelve years back
all the way to yesterday.
Everybody, thank you so much.
That took some getting used to.
But I actually enjoyed it.
'That's me in the spotlight' pretty much
shined the spotlight right on me.
R.E.M.'s success showed Kurt Cobain
it was possible to court a big audience
without sacrificing passion
and authenticity.
I've always thought about R.E.M
as a commercial band in the first place.
They just happen to be a good,
passionate commercial band.
And there've always been
good, passionate bands in rock 'n roll
throughout the history.
It's just up to fans and people
involved in the music industry
to make sure that it doesn't get
as stale and as bad
as it has within the last 10 years.
Especially in the Reagan era.
Kurt Cobain was searching for a sound
that could be both
commercial and passionate,
and in the spring of 1991, with
new drummer Dave Grohl in the band,
Nirvana hit on a musical dynamic
that would send a buzz of excitement
through their rehearsals.
What we would do is we would go in
to this rehearsal space to write songs,
and the first half an hour of every
practice we would just freeformed jam,
just go for it.
Sometimes it was total noise,
and sometimes there was a song there.
But so what we would do is
we would see how quiet we could get
and to see how loud we could go.
There's that whole dynamic
of loud-quiet, loud-quiet.
Maybe that's what you get when you
combine heavy riff rock with pop music,
and then you have a song that
actually has a big hook chorus
and you have a heavy loud rock band
that just really pushes it forward.
# Taken time is
# All but true
# You're the reason
# I feel pain
# Feels so good to
# Feel again
It was a sound that Kurt Cobain
had always dreamed of,
noise and melody, hard guitars
and harmonies,
and it first discovered it in the music
of alternative rock's unsung heroes.
Kurt had always talked about
what would happen if you
started a band that melted
Black Sabbath and The Beatles.
So, all along he was just thinking
about aggression and tunefulness.
And that was The Pixies.
# Gouge away
# You can gouge away
# Stay all day
The Pixies had formed in Boston in
1985 and begun crafting a minimal sound
based around the simple dynamic
of quiet-loud.
Quiet in the verse,
loud in the chorus.
Or the other way around.
'Gouge Away' the chorus is....
# Gouge away
# You can gouge away
# Stay all day
# If you want to
And then...
the verse is...
# ... aggravation
# Some sacred questions
# You stroke my locks
The verse is up and then...
# Gouge away
# You can gouge away
What The Pixies did
was take soft and loud
and do all sort of interesting
things in that,
so their guitars kind of veer off.
They're not just going in a straight line.
The Pixies unique sound
owed much the band's
raw, untrained musical imagination,
and bassist Kim Deal's desire
to avoid the usual rock clichés.
A lot of it is our limitations,
like when the end of the song's coming,
I don't know we've ever gone.
I don't think that...
Honestly...
This is one of five maybe- on the hand,
that I have done this
in my life, right there.
I think I did pretty good.
It felt good.
The Pixies minimal approach
was summed up on a classic
song of surreal confusion.
# With your feet in the air...
'Where is my mind'
# Try this trick and spin it, yeah
# Your head will collapse
# But there's nothing in it
# And you'll ask yourself
# Where is my mind
Kim Deal helped propel the song
with a simple base line
resisting the urge to overelaborate.
But you can't believe how
some people cannot do that,
and will not do that.
Especially real base players.
I'm looking at you.
What they'll do
is sort of go...
Because there's this little
drum thing that happens,
or maybe it's a guitar thing.
And they want to help push
every little moment,
they want to be involved.
They won't just
pedal through something.
The Pixies provided the final ingredient
Kurt Cobain had been looking for.
Nirvana had arrived at a sound
that blended the fury of grunge
with a new feel for melody
and the mass commercial appeal of R.E.M.
And in April, 1991,
Nirvana performed a raw
version of a new song
that would draw
all those elements together
to become alternative rock's
defining anthem.
This song is called
'Smells like teen spirit'.
The band built up the drama
and tension in the song
by using the Pixies'
quiet-loud trademark.
What happened was that
we played that riff over and over again,
and then Dave or I would stop.
"Just slow this down.
Like the moment you slow this down
you have a kind of a dynamic."
And once we did that, it made sense.
# Come out and play
# Make up the rules
# I know I hope
# To die the truth
'Smells like teen spirit' I really
remember thinking,
that is such a Pixies rip.
It is, the baseline,
and the chord-key single note
guitar thing over the drums.
I mean it was almost thrown away
at one point just because
just seemed too much
like the Pixies.
# A dirty word
With 'Smells like teen spirit'
Nirvana had the basis for a hit.
But they needed a producer who
could harness their live energy
and shape it into a more
radio-friendly sound.
Actually, truth be told,
I was one of the people that was
on the short list to produce 'Nevermind',
and I passed.
Do you want to stop now?
# ...and contagious
# Here we are now
# Entertain us
# A mulatto
# An albino
The band finally settled on a producer
with underground credentials
and a pop touch,
Butch Vig.
I knew I just wanted to set them up
in a big room and try to capture
the energy in the initial performance.
Make sure that was the most
important thing about the song.
But I also wanted to make it sound
bigger and much more focused
than 'Bleach' was.
In order to achieve a richer sound
on the 'Nevermind' album,
Butch Vig created multiple layers
of Kurt's voice.
A process known as doubletracking
that the singer initially resisted.
He really didn't like
doing things over again,
but he loved The Beatles so I knew
I could use an excuse if I had,
and that was that John Lennon
always doubletracked his vocals.
He hated the sound of his voice
and because Kurt was such a Beatles fan,
every time I used the John Lennon
reference he'd go, "Ok."
# With the lights out
its less dangerous
# Here we are now
# Entertain us
# I feel stupid and contagious
# Here we are now
# Entertain us
'Teen Spirit' was plain
to see in the song's video,
but its title had less
rebellious origins.
The physical sensation.
Teen Spirit.
The only anti-perspirant made
for our generation.
Teen Spirit.
With five fragrances.
Kurt's former girlfriend used
a deodorant called 'Teen Spirit',
prompting a mutual friend
called Kathleen Hanna
to create a historic
piece of graffiti.
So one night we went out and got all
fucked up, me and Kurt and Kathleen Hanna.
And Kathleen had some
spray paint and
in Kurt's bedroom she sprayed,
"Kurt smells like Teen Spirit'.
So it's kind of like saying,
Kurt has coodies,
or Kurt smells like this girl.
But Kurt didn't know that it was
the name of a deodorant
and he just simply saw it and said,
"Oh. Teen Spirit. That's a great line."
And it wasn't until the song actually
came out that somebody said,
"It's strange your wrote a song
about a woman's deodorant."
And he said, "I did?"
# A mulatto
# An albino
Cobain had a surprise
of his own in store
for the end
of the 'Teen Spirit' video.
A shot of a janitor that harked back
to his first job in Aberdeen.
Kurt would continually dwell
on his troubled youth in his music.
And he revisited the darkest hours
he'd spent sleeping rough
in the haunting song
'Something in the way'.
We did 4, 5 takes of the song
and it just didn't happen.
And out of frustration Kurt
walked in the control room
and laid down on the couch,
and started sort of singing the song
and kept playing quieter and quieter,
to the point it was almost a whisper.
# Underneath the bridge
# The tarp has sprung a leak
And I just said,
stop right here,
and I unplugged the phone,
I turned off the air conditioning,
I sealed the doors and said,
everybody stay out of here.
And I brought a couple
of mikes in,
and just recorded him
on the couch.
# And I'm living off of grass
# And the drippings from my ceiling
# It's okay to eat fish
# 'Cause they don't have any feelings
He did live in abandoned houses.
He lived in hallways.
He would go sneak into
the hospital he was born in
and sleep in the waiting room,
because no one would come and say,
why are you here,
they thought he was waiting
for someone.
# Something in the way
And, I swear to God,
when he sang it the first time,
the song is maybe three minutes long,
I swear to God I held
my breath the whole time.
# Something in the way
Kurt Cobain gave a voice
to an audience
who saw the pain and confusion
of their own lives
reflected in his music.
There was a passion and quality
in the recording that sounded
exciting and dangerous
and something they hadn't heard before.
There was an audience out there
that I think had been set up for that,
by bands like R.E.M. or Hüsker Dü
or The Replacements.
And all of a sudden,
to have this record
that sort of encapsulated all those bands
and so many things at the same time,
it had this sheer energy
and this intense impact,
people went crazy for it.
In January, 1992,
'Nevermind' finally topped the US charts.
The outsiders had won.
Grunge fever began in earnest
as bands like Pearl Jam and
Smashing Pumpkins joined the party.
The mainstream media scented
a youth cult right for exploitation.
Being fashionable used to mean
looking good.
Well, thanks to a fad that
started in the Pacific Northwest,
high fashion now means...
Well, you decide.
Grunge is the fashion trend launched
by the hard driving guitar music
known as the Seattle sound.
The grunge look is an urban-lumberjack-
anything-goes ensemble
of duck boots, tattered shirts,
and long underwear.
And the grunge is spreading
to the trendy Hollywood health spots.
Even the New York fashion shows.
This is the spring look
for 1993.
It basically created
a huge spasm of greed.
Labels wanted desperately to sign
another band like Nirvana.
Where there's one
there must be more.
Let's sign everybody we can.
Seattle definitely lost its innocence
in a lot of ways.
Kurt Cobain felt that loss
of innocence personally
as he was thrust into the spotlight.
Fame and fortune provided
little consolation.
You can't buy happiness, I mean,
that made me happy for a little while,
but I was probably just as happy with,
I don't know...
I look back on going to second-hand
stores and stuff like that,
and finding a little treasure like that,
and that actually meant more to me
because it was more
of a stab in the dark.
All of a sudden he's got
that MTV crowd.
Like, "Whoooo!
I'm multi-platinum?
"Everywhere I go I'm now mobbed?
"I still go to the Salvation Army
store to buy my clothes
"but I can't go in now
"because they know I go there so
there's like 80 kids waiting in front.
"To see what I'm gonna buy.
"And they've pressed up to the glass so
much they cracked the glass of the store."
This was all happening
to that guy.
Some people can handle it,
some people can't.
Kurt Cobain wasn't the only one longing
for a simpler, more innocent time.
From their hometown of Athens, Georgia,
R.E.M had watched alternative rock
grow from a tiny independent community
into a fully-fledged
commercial enterprise.
And they now began to craft
an album that took stock
of what had been won and lost
on the way.
My grandparents were
getting very old
and I was reflecting a lot
on death, and passage
and sorrow and mourning
and all this stuff.
And that really influenced the material
for 'Automatic for the people'.
It's a pretty sombre record,
but quite beautiful, I think.
And it captured something
very real.
'Automatic for the people'
is steeped in memories
and one song based around Mike Mill's
simple piano refrain
harked back to the golden days
of the band's youth.
Honestly I think we were here
in this very studio,
and I was playing it and I wasn't
really thinking anything of it.
I was just doing it because it was
something I had and I was working on,
and Michael heard it and said,
"Keep going, keep going."
And I think he heard something
that took him to a place.
It was actually somewhat autobiographic.
It came from a real thing.
# I forgot my shirt at the water's edge
# The moon is low tonight
A lot of people in Athens had parties
and then at 2 in the morning
everyone would go out to a pond
or a lake and jump in the water,
get drunk and sleep with each other.
That was kind of the inspiration
for the song 'Nightswimming'.
# Nightswimming deserves a quiet night
# I'm not sure all these
people understand
# It's not like years ago,
# The fear of getting caught,
# Of recklessness and water
'Nightswimming' was infused
with the spirit of Athens, Georgia,
but the band decided to put
the finishing touches to the album
in the new music capital of Seattle,
where a friendship would blossom
between R.E.M. and Nirvana.
Peter had moved to Seattle
and had become friends with
this band called Nirvana.
We went out there to make the record,
to finish the record
and ended up hanging out
with those guys a lot.
They were so awesome and cool.
They loved R.E.M. and we loved
what they had done.
It was a great moment in time.
Michael Stipe would
even become godfather to
Kurt Cobain and his wife
Courtney Love's daughter.
Kurt himself told me that the band
he had come to admire most was R.E.M.
Because everything they had achieved
they had done it without compromise.
And he had seen everything
that he had been a part of
suddenly become part of
this machine that he despised.
And there was nothing
he could do about it.
Michael Stipe recognised the kindred
spirit in Kurt Cobain,
but one whose emotional honesty
left him vulnerable.
Kurt Cobain had this incredible
sensitivity...
It's kind of what did him in
in the end, really,
he was just a very delicate creature,
for a lot of reasons.
But he was very real,
and he showed his emotion
very clearly in his work.
And a lot of that emotion was
just incredible rage and anger.
That rage boiled over
in the spring of 1993,
as Kurt Cobain grappled
with the responsibilities
of fatherhood and stardom,
and the demons of depression
and addiction.
With just a trace of grim irony
Kurt joked that Nirvana's next album
would be called
'I hate myself, and I want to die'.
# 'Cause everybody hurts...
It's as if the moment he reached
that pinnacle stardom
it was too bright
and he had to drop it,
and he began retreating
from that moment on.
Moving away from stardom,
moving away from all that he had sought,
and moving deeper and deeper
into drugs.
You don't have to be Freud
to analyse
that clearly there was something
about getting what he wanted
that made him still feel unfulfilled.
Eventually released as 'In Utero',
the album featured darkly
tender love songs
and thinly veiled attacks
on the music business.
# Teenage angst has paid off well
# Now I'm bored and old
'Serve the servants' is a lot about...
I mean, the first opening lines
that say 'Teenage angst has paid off well
now I'm bored and old',
that is certainly about my ideas
about grunge rock
and what I've experienced
in the last few years.
Kurt was still torn between
the underground and the mainstream,
rock and pop, rage and melody.
'In Utero' may have alienated
some of the fans of 'Nevermind'
but Kurt never lost his gift
for creating music with the potential
to reach a global audience.
That gift was glimpsed
for one last time
during an extraordinary MTV
acoustic concert
later turned into an album
by R.E.M. Scott Litt.
'Nirvana Unplugged'.
# Come as you are
# As you were
# As I want you to be
The rehearsals were a catastrophe.
Everybody there thought
this show is not gonna happen.
Kurt was struggling
with drug withdrawal.
# Take your time
Even the ever reliable Dave Grohl
struggled at first.
It didn't sound good.
Usually I have these massive
fat sticks
and I beat the hell out of the drums.
And I got these little cocktail
drum set and we'd
run through a song and
Kurt would turn to me and say,
"Do you think you can
play a little bit softer?"
"Yeah sure. I'll play little bit softer."
And at the end of the song
he'd go, "Yeah, just bring it down
a little bit more. A tiny bit."
All right, so I'd just barely...
And he'd turn around and say,
"Just a little bit more."
"What the fuck am I doing here?
I won't play if you don't want me to.
"I'll shake a rattler or something."
But the MTV producer was on hand
to spare Dave Grohl's blushes.
We got to the gig and the producer said,
"Have you ever tried these?"
And he just hands me these sticks
like bundles of chopsticks or something.
"Hotrods", yeah, they're made up
of these little wooden dowels
and it's got a flappy kind of sound.
Basically the sharpness
is diffused.
# Memoria
I'll never forget after we did
'Unplugged' how happy Kurt was.
He was so happy.
He was this person right there
on the center.
He was really, really happy after that.
He was relieved and...
We pulled it off.
That happiness would be short-lived.
Behind the scenes Kurt
was beginning to unravel,
tormented with depression
and heroin addiction.
He attempted suicide in Rome
just four months later.
The last couple of months
of Kurt's life were a train wreck.
People were doing the best
they could to get him help,
but it's almost a spiritual
question that gets raised,
what can you do for somebody
who, at that point,
is so much wanting
to destruct their own lives?
Members of the music
community tried to offer support.
R.E.M.'s Michael Stipe, gravely
concerned at unfolding events,
made a desperate
attempt to rescue Kurt
from his spiraling descent.
We talked about collaborating.
It was really in the last
days of his life.
I created a... in an attempt to pull him
out of the headspace he was in in Seattle,
in this house, all alone,
the last weeks.
I created a project that he had
to fly to Georgia to work with me on
and we had a deadline
and bla, bla, bla...
It was really just an attempt
to pull him out of
the headspace space that he was in
and it didn't work.
Sadly.
Despite last edge interventions
by those closest to Kurt Cobain
the singer was found dead in
his Seattle home on April the 8th, 1994.
He had shot himself
three days earlier.
When Police arrived, they found
a suicide note quoting Neil Young's lyric,
'It's better to burn out
than fade away',
and the stereo still turned on.
What we do know, when he died,
that R.E.M. was the last CD
in his CD player.
The Police found the CD player on
and they found R.E.M. in it.
Now, whether that was
the last thing he listened to,
there's some degree
of speculation about that.
We do know, of course,
what he said in the suicide note.
And in my years as a journalist
I don't think I've ever felt
more haunted than actually looking
at the suicide note
and seeing how hard he had
pressed down with his pen
to make sure that his words
were clearly read.
Just three years after alternative rock
had achieved his greatest triumph,
it had lost its most iconic,
enigmatic figurehead.
To some, it almost seemed
that Kurt Cobain had already
recorded his own epitaph.
A haunting version of song
'Where did you sleep last night',
by blues legend Leadbelly,
that captured all the passion,
belief and raw emotion
that alternative rock had so
dramatically reclaimed for its audience.
# My girl, my girl, don't lie to me,
# Tell me where
did you sleep last night
Well, there were some crazy things
again that are filled with
irony about 'Unplugged'.
Kurt wanted lilies.
Basically he set the set up.
It looks like a funeral.
# My girl, my girl, where will you go?
# I'm going where the cold wind blows.
# In the pines, in the pines,
# Where the sun don't ever shine.
# I would shiver the whole night through
# Her husband, was a hard working man,
He ends the show with
the Leadbelly song
and that song basically strips the music
of Nirvana all back to a blues.
And it becomes a requiem.
It's a perfect requiem
for Nirvana.
# But his body never was found.
# My girl, my girl, don't lie to me,
# Tell me where...
After Kurt's death,
Scott Litt had to revisit the singer's
most harrowing performance
as he put the finishing touches
to the 'Unplugged' recordings.
Getting through that song
was the hardest thing.
And those were with me,
Krist and Dave.
And I remember feeling like
there were ghosts in the room.
# My girl, my girl, where will you go?
# I'm going where the cold wind blows.
# In the pines,
# the pines,
#  sun,
# .shine.
# I shiver the whole...
# night through!
It had to end right there.
Right with that scream,
right with that song,
right with that howl.
For those left behind,
there will always be sadness
for the loss of a unique talent,
and regret for what might have been.
If I could change anything
I wish that Kurt was still alive.
That's the only thing.
That's it.
I'm sad that he died so young
because I think he was just
moving out of a phase of writing
into a new phase that I think
might have been extraordinary.
But he didn't make it.
Kurt Cobain was a brilliant artist.
He could have done whatever
he wanted to do,
and been really good at it.
That's it.
Transcription and
synchronization by Fry.