September 24th, 1966,
un unknown figure touches down
in the streets of London
with only a Fender Stratocaster
and a few dollars to his name.
Within days of his arrival,
Jimi Hendrix would turn
the world of music upside down.
Jimi changed the sound of the guitar.
I think in many respects he changed
the sound of rock far
more than The Beatles.
He called himself
a 'voodoo child',
a virtuoso, who in just four
short years,
will take the blues from
the Mississippi delta
to the psychedelic limits
of outer space.
He redefined what it meant
to be a guitar player,
what it meant to be a musician,
I think he redefined what
it meant to be an artist
and he redefined the whole period
in which he existed.
All that stuff that was going on
in the 60s
is channeled through
Jimi Hendrix's music.
You can hear Martin Luther King
being shot in his music,
you can hear bombs falling
on Vietnam in his music,
you can hear bombs exploding in the heads
of an entire generation on LSD
in the music of Jimi Hendrix.
In the end, he himself
will become a victim
of the dark side of the era.
His tragic death bringing
a symbolic end
to the tumultuous 60s.
This is a journey into
the first Age of Rock
seen through the eyes
of his most dazzling icon...
Jimi Hendrix.
When Jimi Hendrix,
a left hander
who played a right handed
guitar upside down,
made his first explosive appearance
in London in 1966,
he sent shockwaves through
the aristocracy of British music.
# Purple Haze all in my brain,
# lately things don't seem the same,
# actin' funny but I don't know why
# 'scuse me while I kiss the sky.
I saw him perform with everybody else.
With Eric Clapton, boy, you name it,
they were there.
He came on the stage and
it was just mindblowing.
And I think Eric's comment
after Jimi played was,
"Well, I'm off home
to practice."
I was just glad
I wasn't a guitarist.
Like Eric Clapton,
fellow guitarist Jeff Beck,
was also blown away by Hendrix's
guitar pyrotechnics.
The fact that he was doing things
so upfront and so wild, unchained.
That's what I wanted to do
but being British and
the victim of the class system
or whatever...
the poxy old schools I used to go to,
I couldn't do what he did.
And I just went away
from there thinking,
I'd better think of
something else to do.
He was doing things
that they couldn't do,
because he was picking out a baseline
with his thumb,
a lead with his little finger and
playing rhythm with the rest of it.
It was a kind of three-man group
on one guitar.
The roots of rock lie deep
in the blues of the Mississippi delta.
This music cast a powerful spell
on Jimi Hendrix.
Growing up in Seattle in the 50s,
he got his first guitar aged 12,
spending his teens learning the licks
of the twelve-bar blues.
# Well I wait around the train station
# Waitin' for that train
The blues has always been there
way before it was ever called the 'blues'.
It's a strand of music... it's a note
that resonates throughout the human race.
In order to escape a jail term
for riding in a stolen Cadillac,
Hendrix elected to join
the 101st Airborne Division.
It was in the Army that Hendrix
began experimenting
with the sounds of electric
rhythm & blues.
Muddy Waters, Howlin' Wolf
and BB King were the godfathers of R&B,
and this electrically charged music
would underpin
the early career of Jimi Hendrix.
Hendrix's time in the military
was troubled and didn't last long.
The end came not long after he was
discovered sleeping with his guitar.
Discharged from the Army in 1962,
a pennyless Hendrix
found work as a guitar for hire
on the black R&B network
known as the Chitlin' Circuit.
It was this alternate nether universe
that happened
that most white people
would never experience
or never even know it happened.
It happened when
all the white people were asleep,
then in this little town,
these bands would come out an put on
these incredible shows.
Hendrix spent almost 4 years
on that circuit
playing with a variety
of different bands.
All I remember is getting out
of the Army
and then trying to get
something together,
and then I was playing in different groups
all around the States and Canada.
Playing behind people
most of the time.
He toured alongside the likes of Ike
and Tina Turner, BB King, James Brown...
If he wasn't actually on stage
with these people
he would be in the wings
watching and learning.
Hendrix did a stint as a sideman
to Little Richard
whose flamboyance was an inspiration
to the young guitarist.
Hendrix said, "I want
to do with the guitar
what Little Richard
does with his voice."
Jimi Hendrix's perseverance to go on...
he didn't mind looking freaky,
like I don't mind it, 'cause I was
doing it before he was.
And I know when he saw me
gave him confidence,
and great recompense or reward.
My Lord!
4,000 miles away in Britain
the R&B Hendrix was playing
on the Chitlin' Circuit
was finding a devoted following.
# I love the way you walk
White musicians were
interpreting this music
in ways that would in turn prove a key
influence on Jimi Hendrix.
# ... I got my eyes on you
It was playing blues that thawed out
the emotional permafrost
of 1950s post-war English austerity.
Because of its emphasis on improvisation,
it unlocked the creativity
of the young musicians who
cut their teeth on it.
Everybody starting out just copied
the records they listened to note for note.
I was trying to sing like Howlin' Wolf.
But from this copying
we learnt the roads.
Tell us something about him, Brian.
When we first started playing together
because we wanted to play R&B
and Howlin' Wolf was one
of our greatest idols.
It's a great pleasure to find
him booked in this show tonight.
- It really is a pleasure.
- Thanks for Howlin's records.
So I think it's better that we shut up
and we have Howlin' Wolf on stage.
# How many more years
# Have I got to let you dog me around
We based everything we did
from our knowledge of
starting as a blues band.
# If you see my little red rooster
# Please drive him home
Formed in 1962,
The Rolling Stones took their name
from a classic Muddy Waters' song.
# If you see my little red rooster
The early shows, their sort
of embryonic period,
they just played blues covers.
They had no real material of their own,
so to speak, early on.
The key of course was
when they began writing.
And when they did,
they used these blues influences
and filtered it through
their own experience.
'Satisfaction' is really one
of the first great Stones' songs.
It's a song that Muddy Waters
would have been happy to write.
I think it would rank
as a great blues song
even if it had come from one
of those guys on Chess Records.
# I can get no satisfaction
# I can't get no girl reaction
'Satisfaction' is basically a blues,
you know, it's just a different form.
I was just that...
# I can get no satisfaction
# I can get me know satisfaction
# 'cause I try and I try, yeah I try
# I can get no...
The sexual swagger of 'Satisfaction'
pointed the way
to a new direction in music.
Electric blues music was morphing
into something distinctly British.
# And I'm tryin' to make some girl
They pretty much adapted pop-art ideas
to their blues-based R&B
and, in a way, invented rock music
just by putting pop and R&B together
in a cheeky funny way,
with a great backbeat
and a blast off of a riff.
Now the blues was being
reexported back to America
introducing the mainstream
to a music they'd previously ignored.
We, the young kids in London
and Newcastle and Liverpool,
were responsible for putting
a hand inside America's garbage can
and pulling out culture which
they were trying their best to crush.
All this was a revelation
to Jimi Hendrix.
In 1965 he left the Chitlin' Circuit
and moved to New York
where he discovered a new world
of white music coming out of the UK.
Imagine Hendrix walking down somewhere
where there's an import record store.
Somebody's just got all these weird
records from England,
records by people like the Yardbirds...
where guitar players like Jeff Beck
are pursuing many of the same things
that Hendrix himself was working on
to do with feedback, distortion,
and in some cases maybe taking it further
than Hendrix himself had at that time.
The guitarists that most
impressed Hendrix
were Jeff Beck of the Yardbirds
and Eric Clapton.
Clapton had gained
a formidable reputation
playing with John Mayall
and the Bluesbreakers.
English guitar players showed us, not just
how to play the guitar in a certain way,
but they showed us how it looked.
And how it could be sexy,
how it could be forceful.
They were clearly taking influences
from America
but they were showing us something
that we really didn't
know that much about.
It wasn't only British
guitar experimentation
that was to shape the music
of Jimi Hendrix.
While living in Harlem he fell
under the spell of an unlikely hero,
Bob Dylan.
Jimi took a copy of 'Blowin' in the wind'
to a Harlem discotheque,
totally African-American
experience at the time,
brought this in, went
up to the DJ and said,
"I've got this great new track.
Let's play it."
So the DJ puts the song
and the immediate response,
everyone was dancing and then
'Blowin' in the wind', "How many...",
Everyone stops, they all look at Jimi,
and Jimi literally
has to run from the club for his life.
# Johnny's in the basement
# Mixing up the medicine
# I'm on the pavement
# Thinking about the government
# The man in the trench coat
# Badge out, laid off
# Says he's got a bad cough
# Wants to get it paid off
# Look out kid
# It's somethin' you did
# God knows when
# But you're doin' it again
# You better duck down the alley way
# Lookin' for a new friend
# The man in the coon-skin cap
# In the big pen
# Wants eleven dollar bills
# You only got ten
The song that would define
Dylan in his prime
and be pivotal in
the development of Jimi Hendrix
is 'Like a Rolling Stone',
a tour-de-force that
revolutionized rock music.
One of the most exciting
things about it
is that opening "bang"
on the snare.
You know, it's like a gavel,
a judge wackin' the gavel on his desk,
saying, "Ok, History is called to order."
# Once upon a time you dressed so fine
# You threw the bums a dime
in your prime, didn't you?
That's how special, I think the people
involved in that song,
not just only Dylan but the producer,
the musicians, everyone knew.
# You used to laugh about
They say it's the greatest record
of all times.
It's amazing to have played on that.
I knew that this stuff would be regarded
as something other than another record.
# Once upon a time you dressed so fine
# You threw the bums a dime
in your prime, didn't you?
# People'd call, say,
"Beware doll, you're bound to fall"
The character of Dylan's voice
struck a chord with Jimi,
encouraging Hendrix to believe
that he too could make it as a singer.
Hendrix had always been
very self-conscious about his singing.
He'd worked behind
a lot of great singers,
and on the same bill
as a lot of great singers,
and he barely considered
himself a singer at all.
But when he heard Dylan, he thought,
"Well, if this guy can sing, so can I."
# How does it feel
# To be on your own
# With no direction home
Hendrix heard Dylan and realised
that if a voice has character
then it really doesn't matter if
it's a conventional "good voice" or not.
If you sound like yourself
and you sound like you mean it,
then you can sing rock 'n roll.
# Got a feeling inside
It was The Who,
an uncompromising, loud
and aggressive London band,
that would feed most directly
back into the act of Jimi Hendrix.
Their high octane performances
gave rock a harder edge.
I think the first band
that I ever truly believed
was and out-and-out rock band
that I saw was The Who.
When I saw The Who
play at the Marquee
there was a unity about what they did
with the base, guitar and drums...
and it said to me, this is different,
this is not blues, it's something else.
I wouldn't have been able
to categorise it as 'rock' at that time,
but that's really what it was.
We were doing feedback
and all that stuff onstage,
which came out of putting
all this stuff in a pot, stirring it up,
getting bored with this bit,
doubling up the beat,
banging on a note,
wanging on a chord
and turning the amp until
it fed back and...
away you go.
# People try to put us d-down
(Talkin' 'bout my generation)
# Just because we get around
# Things they do look awful c-c-cold
(Talkin' 'bout my generation)
# I hope I die before I get old
In 'My Generation' they had that
incredible stutter, you know,
"Why don't you all f-f-f..."
# Why don't you all f-fade away
(Talkin' 'bout my generation)
# And don't try to d-dig what we all say
The stuttering on that record,
I thought was brilliant phrasing.
That was their debut in America,
so you heard the record and you went,
"He's gotta be putting that on."
That couldn't be a guy
that actually stuttered.
It was interesting.
# I'm just talkin' 'bout my g-g-generation
(Talkin' 'bout my generation)
The stutter on 'My Generation' reflects
the frustration and the anger
in the attitude of the song.
It's a 'fuck you' moment.
This was a complete homage to
the inarticulateness of rebellious youth,
who couldn't speak,
they could hardly think.
It's like the old line,
"What are you rebelling against?"
"Well, what have you got?"
The Who were actually pivotal
in the development of the new rock.
Remember that rock performance
was still more or less in its infancy
when the Stones started out in the clubs
they were all sitting on stools.
But with The Who there was
an element of real danger.
The Who completely altered
notions of rock performance,
and also the way that a basic
three instrument band
could look and sound.
The Who's total mastery of the stage
and somewhat destructive tendencies
anticipated the wilder
excesses of rock to come.
Jimi Hendrix, for one,
would borrow heavily from The Who's
incendiary style of performance.
He certainly took an awful
lot of what The Who were doing.
The feedback stuff from Townsend,
he made it his own thing.
But it was kind of weird seeing
a black guy come over from America
and look at what we were doing
and take it into his own thing.
So the whole thing
had gone a circle.
By mid 1966,
Hendrix was going it alone,
playing the clubs
in Greenwich Village.
He wasn't making much money
but he was gathering a cult audience.
Whispers began to circulate
about an extraordinary talent.
I once went to the 'Cafe Wha?'
in the Village,
that's when I first saw Jimi Hendrix,
and I went, Wow!
This guy is good!
Among the early Hendrix fan club
was Chas Chandler,
the base player of The Animals,
who in the early 60s
had been at the forefront of
the British invasion of America.
When Chandler discovered
Hendrix in New York
The Animals had already broken up.
Chas had gone into management
and was looking for an artist
to cover a Tim Rose folk song,
called 'Hey Joe'.
# Hey Joe, where you goin'
with that gun in your hand
The night Chandler turned up
at the Cafe Wha?
he was stunned, not only
by Hendrix's virtuosity,
but also by his choice of song.
# Hey Joe, where you goin'
with that gun in your hand
The first song Jimi
played was 'Hey Joe',
and I was like, you know,
I wasn't really conscious
of the rest of the act.
I saw a master guitar player.
I saw the best guitar player
I'd ever seen in my life.
It was that obvious, you know,
I just sat there and went, "Puh!"
Let's come to England.
Let me bring him to England.
Hendrix would come to London
on one condition.
He actually said,
"If I go to England with you,
"can you introduce me
to Jeff Beck and Eric Clapton?"
And said, "They're pals of me.
I've known them 2-3 years."
That was the only question he asked.
When Hendrix landed in England
in September 1966,
this was ground central
for not just music,
but for fashion, photography,
film making, this was...
swinging London in its prime
and Jimi showed up
at the single, most opportune moment
he could have shown up in history.
# In the white room with black curtains
near the station.
When Hendrix arrived in London,
Cream were the biggest act in town.
A power trio comprised of blues
jamming legends Eric Clapton,
bassist Jack Bruce,
and Ginger Baker on drums.
# Dawn-light smiles on you leaving,
my contentment.
We considered ourselves
to be 'the cream'.
We were the guys who could play.
Musically we were streets ahead
of any of the others.
If we had played music written
by Humpty Dumpty and Mickey Mouse,
it would still have been fantastic
because of the musicians playing it.
# You said no strings
could secure you at the station.
We were very competitive, at that age,
we were like gunslingers or something.
I wanted to be the best, most frightening
base player in the world,
and I think I was.
I think I succeeded in that.
I was certainly the loudest.
We would take the language of the blues
and apply it to modern music.
In other words, be very arrogant
about it and nick it,
but not nick actual songs,
we just nicked the feeling and
the language of the blues and used that.
Which is very much what
we ended up doing.
What marked this band
as the cream of London,
was their flair for improvisation,
playing solos that never seemed to end.
We simply couldn't stop playing.
None of us was the band leader
so no one would say "Stop. Enough!"
If one of us took off,
let him go.
And we'd just go off that direction,
or go off in that direction.
We were very much pioneers
of that kind of music.
We built that audience
from nothing really,
and the bands that followed us
reaped the benefits of
the work that we had done.
Such was Clapton's
prowess on the guitar,
fans proclaimed his divinity
on the streets of London.
But the guitar god was soon
to be challenged by one of his disciples.
Having been in London
for just a week,
Jimi went along to a Cream gig,
and put in an audacious request
to jam with Clapton.
Nobody gets up to jam with Cream.
Cream is Mount Olympus,
Cream is the absolute pinnacle.
Ordinary mortals cannot breathe
that rarified air that exists
in this hallowed space.
The very brave person
who would do that...
As far as I remember,
he plugged in to my base amp
and did a version of 'Killing floor'.
A blues all the way of course.
Clapton always loved the song
but always thought it was too difficult.
And Hendrix just rages through it,
and does all his tricks and stunts,
the kind of things that people like
Little Richard and The Isley
Brothers hated him doing.
He plays the guitar behind his head,
between his legs, with his teeth...
Feedback, tremolo arm,
dive bombs, the whole works.
He just played his arsehole basically.
The first time I saw Eric I thought,
"Ah, there's a master guitar player."
But Eric was a guitar player,
Jimi was some sort of force of nature.
Eric just stands there and plays
and then we got this guy, you know,
on his knees and playing with his teeth
and screwing the guitar onstage,
and I thought, "God! What is this?"
It was like, Wow!, that kind of thing.
I know it had a
tremendous effect on Eric.
And Eric's hands were
like this on the guitar
and they just dropped and he said...
He just stood there looking at Jimi.
He walked off the stage
and I thought,
"I knew this was gonna happen."
And everybody's just going, "My God!"
It's like word goes around,
"This guy got up to jam with Cream
and he cut Clapton,
he killed god, man!"
I ran backstage and Eric was
standing trying to light a cigarette.
And his hands were shaking
and he just says,
"Is he really that good?"
Chas Chandler was quick to exploit
Jimi's sensational appeal,
stealing the thunder of Cream,
he put his own power trio together,
flanking Hendrix with
two English musicians,
Mitch Mitchell on drums
and Noel Reading on base,
to create
'The Jimi Hendrix Experience'.
# Hey Joe, where you goin'
with that gun in your hand
# Hey Joe, I said where you goin'
'Hey Joe', the song Chas Chandler
had heard Hendrix perform
in obscurity in New York
just six months earlier,
entered the UK top ten
in December 1966.
It was to be the launchpad
for a meteoric career.
The show he played in America
before he went to England...
there were 12 people there.
England a month later, he's attracting
crowds of several hundred.
Six months later,
he's the biggest star in the world.
No artist, I would argue,
in the history of rock
has become famous so quickly.
# One pill makes you larger
# And one pill makes you small
By the mid point of
the summer of love in 1967,
Jimi Hendrix was the toast of London
and had become the
psychedelic dandy of flower-power.
But in his home country
he was little known.
All that was about to change
when Hendrix got the chance
to play the Monterrey Pop Festival
sharing the bill with The Who.
There was a bit of jockeying
between him and The Who
as to who was to go on when,
because neither band...
Each band had a very healthy
respect for the other's capabilities
and neither of them
wanted to follow the other.
I said to Jimi, "Fuck it!
We're not going to follow you on."
So he said, "I'm not going
to follow you on."
So I said, "Listen. We are not
going to follow you on and that's it."
So in the end they resolved
the situation by tossing up a coin.
Townsend won
and opted to go on first.
We didn't get all this 'peace and love'
shit that was going on there.
That was just a load of rubbish.
But the birds were nice.
It was like something from outer space.
Because not only the music
was totally different,
it was played with all
the aggression of a war.
And I think as a piece of theater,
it kind of woke them up.
Only Jimi Hendrix could have
followed us, to be honest with you.
# You know you're
a cute little heartbreaker
# Foxy
# You know you're
a sweet little lovemaker
I think what was so dazzling
about Hendrix
was the sounds he was creating
and the charismatic spell
that he was casting over
the audience was so extreme
that he made everybody else look
as if they were almost trying too hard.
I'd like to bore you for about six
to do a little a thing, you know...
Excuse me for a minute.
Just let me play my guitar, all right?
It was at this point
that Hendrix reached for Bob Dylan,
paying homage to
his song writing hero
with an electrifying performance
of 'Like a Rolling Stone'.
# Once upon a time you dressed so fine
# You threw the bums a dime
in your prime, didn't you?
In a way it was almost
as audacious a thing to do
as burning Clapton
on his own stage was.
Because people left that song alone.
It was one of the all time
monuments of the counter culture.
Hendrix comes on playing
this amazing guitar licks
sort of drawling the song out
in his own inimitable way.
# Look at ya',
a complete unknown
# Like a rolling stone
I was a Dylan fan
but 'Like a Rolling Stone'
was one of these Dylan songs
that sort of escaped me
at the time.
It didn't quite work for me...
by Dylan.
But when Jimi played it
I understood the song.
It clicked with me
for the first time.
The Monterrey audience
was stunned
by the sheer explosive power
of Hendrix's performance.
But more was to follow.
As the cameras rolled,
the voodoo magician
had one final trick
up his sleeve.
There's another great moment
that I remember.
It was a screening of
the Monterey movie,
and happened to be
Eric Clapton and myself
in a little room watching this.
When it came time for
'Wild Thing', which he closed with,
Jimi sneaks and listens to the guitar,
and it's really not very much in tune,
and Clapton yelled,
"Now what are you gonna do?"
And he just turned up the guitar
and showed Clapton
what he was gonna do.
I thought it was an incredible moment.
# Wild thing, you make my heart sing
# You make a everything, groovy
He was such a showman,
and his show was so much
the highlight of Monterrey,
that it got him in
the headlines immediately,
and people were clamouring
to see Jimi Hendrix after that point.
Sacrificing the guitar
at Monterrey
was the defining moment of an artist
who had reached his creative peak.
On that night Jimi Hendrix
became a rock legend.
I was standing right
next to Robbie Shankle,
and I looked around
and his face was like...
in shock.
The audience was shocked too.
That was the whole idea of the act,
to outdo The Who.
Robbie was shocked and disgusted,
you know,
how can a musician take his instrument
and smash it to smithereens.
This is bad karma, man.
To the wide rock audience that saw
Jimi at Monterrey pop
this was the most brilliant show
anybody had ever put on.
When he lit that guitar on fire,
that became one of the seminal
moments of the 60s.
# It was 20 years ago today
# Sgt. Pepper taught the band to play
Hendrix was always looking
for a new direction
and when 'Sgt. Pepper's Lonely
Hearts Club Band' was released in 1967,
he was among the first
to hear its significance.
Having stopped touring in '66,
The Beatles had taken refuge in the studio
to transform themselves from a pop band
into pioneers of psychedelic rock.
What Hendrix saw with
'Sgt. Pepper's'
was a band taking control
of its own musical destiny.
EMI ageing studios at Abbey Road
played a key role in the process.
# We hope you did enjoy the show
The studio at EMI was basically
totally obsolete,
and yet the EMI staff knew
everything about it.
Knew how to push it to its limits
and how to exploit it.
So it's a very English album.
It's like inventing radar in the potting
shed at the end of the garden.
It's very amateurish
and yet they were able to produce
something of genius level from it.
# I read the news today,
oh boy
# About a lucky man who made the grade
It was like a Heath Robinson
sort of situation.
We were tying things together
with bits of string,
and bashing things with hammers
and taping microphones to this,
and putting microphones in water,
you name it, we tried it.
It was always this thing about
guitars not sounding like guitars,
and pianos not sounding
like pianos and so on.
There's more fun in the record
if there's a few sounds
that you don't really
know what they are.
Really they're just instruments,
only something happens on here,
I couldn't tell you what 'cause we have
a special man who sits here
and goes like this...
And the guitar turns into a piano
or something, you know.
And then you always say,
why don't you use a piano?
Because the piano sounds
like a guitar.
# Woke up, got out of bed
# Dragged a comb across my head
They changed everything.
The Beatles were the ones
who changed everything.
'Sgt. Pepper', you could argue
is the most important album of the 60s.
# Found my coat and grabbed my hat
# Made the bus in seconds flat
There was no question that
at the moment it was made,
it was the absolute summation
of everything that had come before
in say, the previous 4 or 5 years.
'Sgt. Pepper' is an entire reflection
of the society at that time.
# Lucy in the sky with diamonds
They were able to... essentially
take drugs without too much censure,
and they could write what they wanted.
The Beatles were tripping
out of their heads.
# Lucy in the sky with diamonds
I think that knocks down
a lot of barriers in your mind.
You say, "Well, you can't play a C sharp
in a C Chord."
But... after you do that,
you can play a C sharp in a C chord.
'Sgt. Pepper' is arguably
their greatest record.
Certainly their most
influential record.
It stunned Jimi Hendrix more
than almost anyone else.
He did, what I think, is the most risky
move he ever did in his entire career.
It was the day after 'Sgt. Pepper's'
had come out,
and Jimi had gotten a copy of it
and learned it.
He came backstage at this concert
and announced to 'The Experience',
we're gonna start our show with a cover
of 'Sgt. Pepper's', the title track.
And Noel Reading told me,
"I just was stunned.
"What do you mean?
This album just came out.
"We're gonna cover someone
else's song?"
And that's what they started
that concert with.
And, to add to it, several of
The Beatles were in the audience.
# It was twenty years ago today,
# Sgt. Pepper taught the band to play
# They've been going in and out of style
# But they're guaranteed
to raise a smile.
The nerve to do that.
Can you imagine anyone
having the guts to,
The Beatles' album has just come out,
universally acclaimed the biggest rock
band in the world that there ever would be,
and for Jimi then to go,
"Ok, the day after it comes out,
"I'm gonna play their song
and do it better."
# Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band.
Hendrix obviously saw that power.
A band that was actually
producing itself now, pretty much.
And said, "Yeah, yeah.
That's for me too."
The Beatles had caught
Jimi's imagination
just as powerfully
as Dylan and The Who.
Through the sonic revolution
of 'Sgt. Pepper',
Hendrix saw the potential
of the recording studio,
believing it could help take his guitar
to a higher level.
# I love your gypsy eyes
In 1968, he started recording
'Electric Ladyland'.
# Way up in my tree
I'm sitting by my fire
'Electric Ladyland'
is Hendrix the producer,
Hendrix fully embracing the capabilities
of the recording studio
and exploring the kind of soundscapes
he could create in the studio
to try to realise on tape the extraordinary
sonic visions he was hearing in his head.
One of the high points
of 'Electric Ladyland'
found Jimi once again acknowledging
a musical debt
with an apocalyptic version
of Dylan's 'All Along The Watch Tower'.
# "There must be some way out of here,"
said the joker to the thief,
# "There's too much confusion,
I can't get no relief.
Hendrix had actually
created the scenario itself.
Dylan had written the scenario,
Hendrix filled in all the colours.
Even Dylan admitted at one point
that 'All Along The Watch Tower'
as Hendrix envisioned it was beyond
the song he had written and recorded.
That song, it's as if Jimi wrote it.
You just get the sense.
It's like the song
he was made to play.
Although 'Electric Ladyland'
would be acclaimed a masterpiece,
the studio where it was recorded
became a curse.
Hendrix's heavy intake of drugs
began to take its tall.
Some tracks took over 50 takes,
and the album hundreds of hours
of recording time.
Things were getting quite freaky.
This was peculiar times.
There was an awful lot of...
unauthorised substances flying around
with different people and all the rest of it.
You were turning up in the studio
and try to mix tracks
and there was 30 and 40 people
turned up as hangers-on.
It was very difficult to be able to talk
about the next step of your life because
most of the people were out of
their minds at the time, you know.
I just thought, "This is crazy.
I'm spending half my time in the day
"trying to talk common sense
to people and...
"all they want to do
is get out of their minds."
I said, "Well. I'm off back to England.
"When you come to your
senses give us a ring."
Minus his manager,
Jimi was left to face the future
without the guiding light
that had led him to stardom.
By 1968, the idealism and promise
of 'flower-power' had begun to fade.
America was bogged down
in Vietnam and at war with itself.
Torn apart by assassinations
and the civil rights struggle.
Europe also saw rioting
on the streets.
The drugs got heavier
and so did the music,
reflecting the paranoia
and tension in the air.
You could just feel it.
It was very, very different.
The whole atmosphere changed.
Became much more politicised, I think.
No longer could you just be a happy
flower child skipping through Hyde Park
with your daisy chain
and your joss stick
because some cop would come along
and bang you on the head.
Whereas in '67 it was
all ok, you know.
They'd even light
your joint for you.
Mick Jagger and Keith Richard
of course have great instincts
for trends and what's going on.
And by 1968 they could see
the trend was for this endarkenment.
The music had to turn darker in response
to the darkness
of the times, 1968 and '69.
So, to their great credit, The Rolling
Stones perfectly synched into that.
# Oh, a storm is threatning
# My very life today
# If I don't get some shelter
# Oh yeah, I'm gonna fade away
# War, children, it's just a shot away
# It's just a shot away
The Stones are one
of the few bands that
that darkness kind of gives them
a new creative zenith.
There was a different
world going on there,
but the Stones were
not afraid to embrace,
and somewhat make
that their mistress.
When you listen to
'Sympathy for the Devil'
it's not like this is a hidden meaning.
You have some people are taking records
and playing them backwards
to look for satanic messages.
With the Stones it's right there.
They're not afraid to touch on
that darkness.
# Please allow me to introduce myself
# I'm a man of wealth and taste
# I've been around for a long, long year
# Stole many a man's soul and faith
They're the band, strangely,
that survives and actually feeds off
the dark drug elements that came in
and destroyed the rest of the scene.
# Please allow me to introduce myself
# I'm a man of wealth and taste
By the time The Rolling Stones
came to play Altamont Festival
in December 1969,
heavy drugs and bad trips
were destroying the hippy dream.
And now Hell's Angels touting
knives and guns were on the scene.
Hired as security, they turned what
was meant to be a peace loving event
into one of the most violent days
in rock history.
A Stones fan was stabbed to death
by a Hell's Angel.
Never had 'Sympathy for the Devil'
seemed a more appropriate song.
We're splitting man if those cats
don't stop beating everybody up inside.
I want them out of the way, man!
I don't like you!
I think the closing of that era
was probably Altamont.
And that really sort of tied it up
with a black bow,
and that's it.
Things got very
business-like after that.
That free spirit died at Altamont.
Altamont had been planned to replicate
the utopian spirit of
the Woodstock Festival
that had taken place in New York St.
just four months before.
It was here that Jimi Hendrix
would make history
unleashing a searing rendition
of the Star-Spangled Banner.
Hendrix climaxed the festival
with this performance of
the Star-Spangled Banner
which, I would say, is the greatest
American work of art
to deal with the Vietnam War
and the titanic struggles
of the civil rights movement,
in any art form
by any artist.
Jimi's tortured take
on the American National anthem
was seen by many
to be a political statement
about the horror the US
was inflicting on Vietnam.
His howling guitar echoing
the sounds of helicopters,
bombs and machine-guns.
This man was in the 101st Airborne
so when you write your nasty letters in...
Nasty letters? Why...?
Well, when you mention
the National Anthem
and talk about playing
it in any unorthodox way,
immediately get a guaranteed percentage
of hate mail from people to say
- how dare...?
- But listen, that's not unorthodox.
- It isn't unorthodox?
- No, no.
I thought it was beautiful,
but then, there you go...
To some critics, the sound
of Hendrix's distorted guitar
was also symbolic of the muddy
reality of Woodstock.
Drenched by torrential rain,
the event hyped as three
days of peace and love
had more the look of a war zone.
We think of this moment as being
the great moment of the 60s.
Everyone coming together.
Oh here's Jimi Hendrix playing.
Well, while he was playing
the Star-Spangled Banner
people are streaming out of the venue.
It's a muddy field.
There are only a handful of people left.
That's the difference
between, of course,
the reality of what it would
have been like to be there,
and the reality of now looking back
at the footage and what we remembered as.
But we as pundits and writers
and film makers go back
and it's hard not
to think of that, in retrospect,
as being the end of a decade.
To Jimi, he left the stage
exhausted and collapsed,
and maybe that's a good metaphor
for what the 60s had become
for everybody at that point.
Jimi Hendrix would never again
match the emotional high of Woodstock.
Burnt out on drugs and exhaustion,
he'd become tired of
the attention-grabbing stage tricks
that audiences constantly
demanded of him.
I don't care, man.
I don't care what they say any more.
It's up to them. If they want to mess up
the evening by looking at one thing...
Because all that is included, man,
when I feel like with my teeth
I do it. because I feel like it.
When I'm onstage, I'm a complete
natural, more so than
talking to a group of people
or something.
By August 1970,
the sparkle had gone.
Hendrix returned to England
to play the Isle of Wight Festival.
Dosed heavily on LSD, he gave
a lacklustre performance.
It would be the his last appearance
in the country that had made him a star.
I was actually at that show
and I'd been waiting,
like everybody else,
for Hendrix to come on
and lift our spirits,
set light to the whole event.
But when he came on. it seemed like
everything was going wrong.
He seemed exhausted, he was having
sort of to drag out all his old songs,
his gear was malfunctioning.
He couldn't get the sound
he wanted out of his amps.
You could almost see the life
ebbing out of him the longer he's onstage.
There was an awful finale, see,
to the whole thing.
Remember Jim Morrison was dead,
Janis Joplin was dead,
The Beatles had broke up,
it seemed like
all the furniture of the 60s
was being put out
on the pavement outside.
On the morning of
September 18th, 1970,
almost exactly 4 years to the day
he'd first arrived in London,
Jimi Hendrix was found dead
in the basement of the Samarkand Hotel
in Notting Hill.
# And the clowns have all gone to bed
His death was undignified,
drowned in vomit,
unconscious from
a combination of red wine
and an accidental
overdose of sleeping pills.
He was 27 years old.
Jimi Hendrix was a weak man,
that was his problem.
And the weakness made him vulnerable.
And vulnerable people in
rock music don't last long.
There might be good people,
there might be nice people,
but they don't last...
You've gotta be tough
in the rock music business
to survive.
The night that he died,
I was supposed to meet him
at the Lyceum to see Sly Stone play,
and I brought with me
a left handed Stratocaster,
I'd just found it.
I think I bought it at Orange Music.
I'd never seen one before
and I was gonna give it to him.
And he was in a box over there
and I was in a box over here
and I could see him
but we never got together.
The next day he was gone and I was
left with that left handed Stratocaster.
The death of Jimi Hendrix
was the final curtain.
Drawing to a close an unprecedented
period of creativity.
The 60s had given birth
to the First Age of Rock.
Presiding over it all, was the genius
and showmanship of Jimi Hendrix.
Jimi Hendrix would prove
a hard act to follow.
# Well, I stand up next to a mountain
# And I chop it down
with the edge of my hand
Next week on
Seven Ages of Rock,
rock reinvents itself
with Pink Floyd and David Bowie.
To find out more about
'The Seven Ages of Rock'
and see some extra stories featuring
artists in the series,
go to "bbc.co.uk/sevenages".
Transcription and
synchronization by Fry.